<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<text>
<body>
<termEntry>
	<langSet xml:lang="en">
		<ntig>
			<termGrp>
				<term>ACADEMIC AWARD LEVEL - PRIMARY</term>
			</termGrp>
		</ntig>
		<descrip type="definition">The award level of the student’s ACADEMIC PROGRAM – PRIMARY.</descrip>
		<descrip type="example">[SIRIS STUDENT element SE035] </descrip>
		<descrip type="example">SIRIS reporting codes are as follows:</descrip>
		<descrip type="example">1  Undergraduate Certificates and Diplomas </descrip>
		<descrip type="example">2  Associate </descrip>
		<descrip type="example">3  Baccalaureate </descrip>
		<descrip type="example">4  Master’s </descrip>
		<descrip type="example">5  Doctoral </descrip>
		<descrip type="example">6  First professional (AuD, DDS, DNP, DPT, DVM, LLM, JD, MD, PharmD, OD) </descrip>
		<descrip type="example">7  Graduate certificate </descrip>
		<descrip type="example">8  Not in a program </descrip>
	</langSet>
</termEntry>
<termEntry>
	<langSet xml:lang="en">
		<ntig>
			<termGrp>
				<term>ACADEMIC PROGRAM – MICROCREDENTIAL</term>
			</termGrp>
		</ntig>
	</langSet>
	<descrip type="definition">The MICROCREDENTIAL being pursued by the student.  Must be a registered microcredential at time of enrollment. </descrip>
	<descrip type="example">[See SIRIS STUDENT element SE045 and SIRIS Degree elements DD010 and DD020] </descrip>
</termEntry>
<termEntry>
	<langSet xml:lang="en">
		<ntig>
			<termGrp>
				<term>ACADEMIC PROGRAM – PRIMARY</term>
			</termGrp>
		</ntig>
		<descrip type="definition">The primary PROGRAM of study being pursued by the student.  Must be a registered APES code at time of enrollment. </descrip>
		<descrip type="example">[See SIRIS STUDENT elements SE030 and SE035 and SIRIS Degree elements DD010 and DD020] </descrip>
	</langSet>
</termEntry>
<termEntry>
	<langSet xml:lang="en">
		<ntig>
			<termGrp>
				<term>ACADEMIC PROGRAM – SECONDARY</term>
			</termGrp>
		</ntig>
		<descrip type="definition">The second (different) PROGRAM of study being concurrently pursued by the student which will result in the awarding of one degree in two (or more) majors.  Must be a registered APES code at time of enrollment.  Secondary Program is used when a student is enrolled in two majors at the same undergraduate award level and the secondary program meets the additional workload requirements to grant two degrees (usually 30 additional hours at the baccalaureate level). </descrip>
		<descrip type="example">[See SIRIS STUDENT element SE040 and SIRIS Degree elements DD010 and DD020 and Appendix R—Guidelines on the Awarding of Two Degrees at the same Level] </descrip>
	</langSet>
</termEntry>
<termEntry>
	<langSet xml:lang="en">
		<ntig>
			<termGrp>
				<term>ACADEMIC RANK</term>
			</termGrp>
		</ntig>
		<descrip type="definition">The academic rank of teaching faculty is designated in accordance with SUNY appointment procedures and is determined by the permanent titles they hold, including Full Professor, Associate Professor, Assistant Professor, Instructor, Lecturer, and Teaching Assistant.  Personnel paid out of temporary service funds, those who contribute their services, and personnel who have no permanent teaching title (e.g. administrators) have no academic rank.  </descrip>
		<descrip type="example">[SIRIS TERM SECTION element TF090] </descrip>
		<descrip type="example">SIRIS reporting codes are as follows: </descrip>
		<descrip type="example">1  Full Professor </descrip>
		<descrip type="example">2  Associate Professor </descrip>
		<descrip type="example">3  Assistant Professor </descrip>
		<descrip type="example">4  Instructor </descrip>
		<descrip type="example">5  Lecturer </descrip>
		<descrip type="example">6  Teaching Assistant </descrip>
		<descrip type="example">7  No Faculty Rank </descrip>
	</langSet>
</termEntry>
<termEntry>
	<langSet xml:lang="en">
		<ntig>
			<termGrp>
				<term>ACCUMULATED CREDIT HOURS</term>
			</termGrp>
		</ntig>
		<descrip type="definition">The number of CREDIT HOURS that a student has successfully completed prior to the current term.  This includes credits earned at his or her present campus and credits earned at other institutions which have been accepted by the reporting institution for the satisfaction of any requirements of a formal award.  Credits granted for experiential learning and credits by examination are also included if they meet the above conditions.  For GRADUATE STUDENTS, this includes only those accumulated credits which can be used to satisfy the requirements of a graduate award.   </descrip>
		<descrip type="example">[SIRIS STUDENT element SE110]  </descrip>
		<descrip type="example">In combination with ACADEMIC PROGRAM – PRIMARY AND HIGHER EDUCATION HISTORY, ACCUMULATED CREDIT HOURS is used be determine STUDENT LEVEL. </descrip>
	</langSet>
</termEntry>
<termEntry>
	<langSet xml:lang="en">
		<ntig>
			<termGrp>
				<term>ADMISSION STATUS</term>
			</termGrp>
		</ntig>
		<descrip type="definition">A student’s admission status as it pertains to the reporting institution.  Codes 1 – 5 are considered the reporting institution’s HOME INSTITUTION STUDENTS.  Codes 6 – 14 are considered non-home institution students, with 6 representing the reporting institution’s continuing education population. </descrip>
		<descrip type="example">[SIRIS STUDENT element SE010] </descrip>
		<descrip type="example">SIRIS reporting codes are as follows:  </descrip>
		<descrip type="example"> 1 Regular Admit – a degree-seeking student admitted into an ACADEMIC PROGRAM having met the institution’s standard academic admissions criteria (default) </descrip>
		<descrip type="example"> 2 Active EOP Special Admit or GOP Recipient– either an UNDERGRADUATE degree-seeking student admitted into an ACADEMIC PROGRAM based on the requirements of the Educational Opportunity Program (EOP) who is receiving direct aid and/or services during the current reporting term or a GRADUATE degree-seeking student receiving support through the Graduate Opportunity Program (GOP) during the current reporting term  </descrip>
		<descrip type="example"> 3 Inactive EOP Special Admit – a degree-seeking student admitted into an ACADEMIC PROGRAM based on the requirements of the Educational Opportunity Program (EOP) who previously received direct aid and/or services from the program but is not receiving them during the current reporting term  </descrip>
		<descrip type="example">4  Other Special Admit – a degree-seeking student admitted into an ACADEMIC PROGRAM based on criteria other than the institution’s standard academic criteria for admission and who is not admitted as an EOP student.  This would include RISK ADMISSIONS, which are students who fail to meet the normal admission standards of the college or students admitted in recognition of a special talent that merits admission into an ACADEMIC PROGRAM offered by the institution that is related to this talent. </descrip>
		<descrip type="example"> 5 Non-degree Seeking – a student who has not MATRICULATED at the college and is not CROSS REGISTERED from another college but is enrolled in at least one CREDIT COURSE (or non-credit course eligible for state aid) </descrip>
		<descrip type="example"> 6 CONTINUING EDUCATION – A student enrolled exclusively in continuing education courses, including those which were approved as remedial.  (Use this code for remedial-course students who should not be included in the reporting campus’s official headcount.). </descrip>
		<descrip type="example"> 7 CROSS REGISTERED Accessory – a student from the affiliate campus who is attending classes at the reporting campus under a CROSS REGISTRATION agreement (applicable only to ESF, Ceramics, and Cornell) </descrip>
		<descrip type="example"> 8 CROSS REGISTERED Another SUNY – a CROSS REGISTERED student from another SUNY college who is attending classes at the reporting campus under a CROSS REGISTRATION agreement </descrip>
		<descrip type="example"> 9 CROSS REGISTERED Non-SUNY/Unknown – a CROSS REGISTERED student from a non-SUNY or unknown campus </descrip>
		<descrip type="example">10 CROSS REGISTERED EXCHANGE STUDENT from abroad – a foreign student attending classes at SUNY under an approved OVERSEAS ACADEMIC PROGRAMS (OAP) EXCHANGE STUDENT program </descrip>
		<descrip type="example">11 COLLEGE IN THE HIGH SCHOOL – STATE OP - For state-operated institutions, a high school student taking one or more college level courses taught in his or her high school with curricular oversight and credit transcript provided by the reporting SUNY institution.  (Community colleges should continue to report these students as Admission Status 1-5.) </descrip>
		<descrip type="example">12 NON-RESIDENT AT NON-NYS LOCATION - A non-resident student exclusively taking courses that are taught outside of New York State and/or the United States   </descrip>
		<descrip type="example">13 AUDITOR - A student enrolled exclusively as an auditor.  Use Special Population Code (SE025) to specifically identify whether the student is a Special Auditor or State-Aidable Auditor. </descrip>
		<descrip type="example">14 EOC (Educational Opportunity Center) - A student enrolled exclusively at a recognized SUNY Educational Opportunity Center.  SUNY universities and colleges are not to use this code. </descrip>
	</langSet>
</termEntry>
<termEntry>
	<langSet xml:lang="en">
		<ntig>
			<termGrp>
				<term>ADVANCED DOCTORAL</term>
			</termGrp>
		</ntig>
		<descrip type="definition">derived STUDENT LEVEL subgroup defined as follows: a STUDENT IN A DOCTORAL DEGREE PROGRAM who (a) holds a master's degree in any field  or who  (b) has accumulated 24 or more semester CREDIT HOURS beyond their bachelor's degree
			Note this is a subset of ADVANCED GRADUATE.</descrip>
		<descrip type="example">The identification of advanced doctoral students is derived from SIRIS STUDENT elements SE030 ACADEMIC PROGRAM – PRIMARY, SP040 HIGHEST EARNED DEGREE, and SE110 ACCUMULATED CREDIT HOURS.  </descrip>
	</langSet>
</termEntry>
<termEntry>
	<langSet xml:lang="en">
		<ntig>
			<termGrp>
				<term>ADVANCED GRADUATE</term>
			</termGrp>
		</ntig>
		<descrip type="definition">A derived STUDENT LEVEL defined as follows: (1)  a STUDENT IN A POST-MASTER’S GRADUATE CERTIFICATE PROGRAM OR 
			(2)a STUDENT IN A DOCTORAL DEGREE PROGRAM who (a) holds a master's degree in any field  or who (b) has accumulated 24 or more semester CREDIT HOURS beyond their bachelor's degree.</descrip>
		<descrip type="example">The identification of advanced graduate students is derived from SIRIS STUDENT elements SE030 ACADEMIC PROGRAM – PRIMARY, SP040 HIGHEST EARNED DEGREE, and SE110 ACCUMULATED CREDIT HOURS.  </descrip>
	</langSet>
</termEntry>
<termEntry>
	<langSet xml:lang="en">
		<ntig>
			<termGrp>
				<term>AIM ASSETWORKS</term>
			</termGrp>
		</ntig>
		<descrip type="definition">AiM is an online Integrated Work Management System (IWMS) developed by AssetWORKS that incorporates property, space, and asset management information into a real-time dynamic database. This system, and its associated data, will be used by many departments within SUNY System Administration, the State University Construction Fund, the Research Foundation, and all campuses for a wide range of users. 
			AiM replaced the BCI/PHYSICAL SPACE INVENTORY (PSI) building information systems previously maintained by SUNY.  The data within AiM will be managed according to updated business processes, with responsibilities divided across campuses, SUNY System Administration, the State University Construction Fund, and the Research Foundation. Visit 
			https://system.suny.edu/capital-facilities/aim-resources/ for more information. </descrip>
	</langSet>
</termEntry>
<termEntry>
	<langSet xml:lang="en">
		<ntig>
			<termGrp>
				<term>AMERICAN COMMUNITY SURVEY</term>
			</termGrp>
		</ntig>
		<descrip type="definition">The U.S. Census Bureau American Community Survey (ACS) helps local officials, community leaders, and businesses understand the changes taking place in their communities. It is the premier source for detailed population and housing information about the United States. Conducted every month, every year. Sent to a sample of addresses (about 3.5 million) in the 50 states, District of Columbia, and Puerto Rico.  The survey asks about topics not on the 2020 Census, such as education, employment, internet access, and transportation. </descrip>
	</langSet>
</termEntry>
<termEntry>
	<langSet xml:lang="en">
		<ntig>
			<termGrp>
				<term>ANNUAL AVERAGE FULL-TIME EQUIVALENT (AAFTE) STUDENT WORKLOAD</term>
			</termGrp>
		</ntig>
		<descrip type="definition">A unit of measure applicable to an academic year and typically derived from attempted CREDIT HOURS in Term Section.  SUNY obtains these student credit hours from the SIRIS TERM SECTION submission.  Currently, the standard AAFTE calculations used by System Administration refer to state-supported AAFTE and are based on activity reported in SIRIS to be state-supported. 
			Generally speaking, one AAFTE workload is equivalent to 30 student credit hours in undergraduate courses or 24 student credit hours in graduate courses.  Health first-professional and doctoral student AAFTEs are based on HEADCOUNT and calculated as follows: one AAFTE for first professionals in the health sciences, one AAFTE for full-time ADVANCED GRADUATE STUDENTS, and .75 AAFTE for part-time ADVANCED GRADUATE STUDENTS.   </descrip>
	</langSet>
</termEntry>
<termEntry>
	<langSet xml:lang="en">
		<ntig>
			<termGrp>
				<term>APES (ACADEMIC PROGRAM ENTERPRISE SYSTEM)</term>
			</termGrp>
		</ntig>
		<descrip type="definition">:  The inventory of all academic programs offered by the State University of New York.  This file contains the official name of each academic program, its approval status, campus, award level, award, and federal (HEGIS, CIP) taxonomic codes.  Where applicable, dates of program deactivation or discontinuance are included.  The APES file is the point of departure for the collection of any data which must be arrayed by program.  Historical, as well as current data, are recorded on the APES file.  Because the APES file contains the University's official list of approved programs, it provides the system-wide review framework for examining requests for program addition or elimination.  It is used to develop annual enrollment and degrees granted statistics for all SUNY institutions by integrating data from SIRIS STUDENT and SIRIS DEGREE.  </descrip>
	</langSet>
</termEntry>
<termEntry>
	<langSet xml:lang="en">
		<ntig>
			<termGrp>
				<term>APES CODE</term>
			</termGrp>
		</ntig>
		<descrip type="definition">This term is used synonymously with the SUNY Academic Program ID, where APES stands for Academic Program Enterprise System.  This code indicates a student’s program of study. </descrip>
		<descrip type="example">[SIRIS STUDENT element SE030 and SE040 (if applicable) and SIRIS DEGREE element DD010]  </descrip>
	</langSet>
</termEntry>
<termEntry>
	<langSet xml:lang="en">
		<ntig>
			<termGrp>
				<term>APPLIED LEARNING</term>
			</termGrp>
		</ntig>
		<descrip type="definition">Applied learning refers to an educational approach whereby students learn by engaging in direct application of skills, theories and models. Students apply knowledge and skills gained from traditional classroom learning to hands-on and/or real-world settings, creative projects or independent or directed research, and in turn apply what is gained from the applied experience to academic learning. The applied-learning activity can occur outside of the traditional classroom experience and/or be embedded as part of a course.
		[See Appendix AB—Criteria for Approved Applied Learning Activities on CONFLUENCE] </descrip>
	</langSet>
</termEntry>
<termEntry>
	<langSet xml:lang="en">
		<ntig>
			<termGrp>
				<term>ATTRITION</term>
			</termGrp>
		</ntig>
		<descrip type="definition">The percentage of students from an entering COHORT who did not earn a degree, are not persisting toward a degree, and did not transfer to another institution by a specific reporting date. </descrip>
	</langSet>
</termEntry>
<termEntry>
	<langSet xml:lang="en">
		<ntig>
			<termGrp>
				<term>AUDITORS (SPECIAL)</term>
			</termGrp>
		</ntig>
		<descrip type="definition">:  See SPECIAL AUDITORS  </descrip>
	</langSet>
</termEntry>
<termEntry>
	<langSet xml:lang="en">
		<ntig>
			<termGrp>
				<term>AUDITORS (STATE-AIDABLE)</term>
			</termGrp>
		</ntig>
		<descrip type="definition">See STATE-AIDABLE AUDITORS </descrip>
	</langSet>
</termEntry>
<termEntry>
	<langSet xml:lang="en">
		<ntig>
			<termGrp>
				<term>AWARD</term>
			</termGrp>
		</ntig>
		<descrip type="definition">The specific degree, diploma, or certificate granted by an institution upon completion of the requirements of a PROGRAM.  Examples include AA, BS, MA, and PhD.   </descrip>
		<descrip type="example">For SIRIS reporting, the award must be coded exactly as it is recorded for each PROGRAM in APES.  </descrip>
		<descrip type="example">[SIRIS DEGREE element DD025] </descrip>
	</langSet>
</termEntry>
<termEntry>
	<langSet xml:lang="en">
		<ntig>
			<termGrp>
				<term>AWARD LEVEL</term>
			</termGrp>
		</ntig>
		<descrip type="definition">:  See ACADEMIC AWARD LEVEL - PRIMARY </descrip>
	</langSet>
</termEntry>
<termEntry>
	<langSet xml:lang="en">
		<ntig>
			<termGrp>
				<term>BEGINNING GRADUATE</term>
			</termGrp>
		</ntig>
		<descrip type="definition">A derived STUDENT LEVEL defined as follows: A student who meets any one or more of following conditions: (1) a STUDENT IN A DOCTORAL DEGREE program who has accumulated fewer than 24 semester CREDIT HOURS beyond their bachelor's degree and does not hold a master’s degree in any field (2) a STUDENT IN A POST-BACCALAUREATE GRADUATE CERTIFICATE PROGRAM (3) a STUDENT IN A FIRST PROFESSIONAL DEGREE PROGRAM (4) a STUDENT IN A MASTER'S DEGREE PROGRAM (5) a GRADUATE STUDENT not admitted to a formal PROGRAM  </descrip>
		<descrip type="example">The identification of beginning graduate students is derived from SIRIS STUDENT elements SE030 PRIMARY ACADEMIC PROGRAM – PRIMARY, SE020 HIGHER EDUCATION HISTORY, SP040 HIGHEST EARNED DEGREE, and SE110 ACCUMULATED CREDIT HOURS. </descrip>
	</langSet>
</termEntry>
<termEntry>
	<langSet xml:lang="en">
		<ntig>
			<termGrp>
				<term>BRIGHTSPACE LEARNING MANAGEMENT SYSTEM</term>
			</termGrp>
		</ntig>
		<descrip type="definition">: The D2L Brightspace platform is the new Digital Learning Environment (DLE) selected for all SUNY campuses, as of Fall 2022. This decision was the result of a multi-year, industry-wide search and the D2L Brightspace Learning Management System will replace the Blackboard Learning Management System (LMS) that was used by many SUNY campuses and other Learning Management Systems used across SUNY. </descrip>
	</langSet>
</termEntry>
<termEntry>
	<langSet xml:lang="en">
		<ntig>
			<termGrp>
				<term>BUSINESS INTELLIGENCE (BI) OR ORACLE BUSINESS INTELLIGENCE (OBI)</term>
			</termGrp>
		</ntig>
		<descrip type="definition">Business Intelligence (BI) comprises the strategies and technologies used by enterprises for the data analysis of business information, to help decision makers and end users make informed business decision. Common functions of business intelligence technologies include reporting, online analytical processing, analytics, data mining, process mining, complex event processing, business performance management, benchmarking, text mining, predictive analytics, and prescriptive analytics. 
		Oracle Business Intelligence (OBI) is a web-based visual analytics tool and interactive dashboard system that consolidates related data to enable decision-makers to create and share analytical reports in a fast, logical, and user-friendly manner.  BI or OBI, utilizes the campus supplied SIRIS data that were loaded into the SUNY Data Warehouse.  The web address to access SUNY OBI is 
		https://www.suny.edu/analytics .  Information about gaining access to OBI can be found on CONFLUENCE</descrip>
	</langSet>
</termEntry>
<termEntry>
	<langSet xml:lang="en">
		<ntig>
			<termGrp>
				<term>CAMPUS IDENTIFIER</term>
			</termGrp>
		</ntig>
		<descrip type="definition">For SIRIS reporting purposes, the unique identifier associated with each SUNY campus as listed in SIRIS Appendix A-1.   </descrip>
		<descrip type="example">[SIRIS STUDENT element SH010, SIRIS COURSE element CH010, SIRIS TERM SECTION element TH010, SIRIS DEGREE element HH040]  </descrip>
	</langSet>
</termEntry>
<termEntry>
	<langSet xml:lang="en">
		<ntig>
			<termGrp>
				<term>CARNEGIE BASIC CLASSIFICATION</term>
			</termGrp>
		</ntig>
		<descrip type="definition">The Basic Classification is an update of the traditional classification framework developed by the Carnegie Commission on Higher Education in 1970 to support its research program. The Basic Classification was originally published for public use in 1973 and subsequently updated in 1976, 1987, 1994, 2000, 2005, 2010, 2015, 2018, and 2021.  The Carnegie Basic Classification is an element on the IPEDS Institutional Characteristics Survey and is used in creating national benchmarking groups by sector. </descrip>
	</langSet>
</termEntry>
<termEntry>
	<langSet xml:lang="en">
		<ntig>
			<termGrp>
				<term>CENSUS DATE</term>
			</termGrp>
		</ntig>
		<descrip type="definition">For typical fall and spring semester calendar instruction, the census date for a particular SECTION is the end of the third week of classes (20 calendar days after the first day of classes).  For quarter calendar instruction, the census date for a particular SECTION is the end of the second week of classes (13 calendar days after the first day of classes).
				It is intended that the census date defines the time in which a stable student population and registration have been achieved.  For summer or mini-terms, the census date of a SECTION is left to the best judgment of the campus administration and should represent a reasonable point of enrollment stabilization which should be no earlier than the point at which 20% of the class work has been completed.  
				In general, a student may be reported if there is a properly verified class attendance on, or subsequent to, (but not merely prior to) the census date.  The usual process of dropping or adding courses must be completed prior to the census date. </descrip>
		<descrip type="example">For submitting official enrollment data on SIRIS STUDENT and SIRIS TERM SECTION</descrip>
		<descrip type="example">[See SIRIS Appendix O on CONFLUENCE for further information] </descrip>
	</langSet>
</termEntry>
<termEntry>
	<langSet xml:lang="en">
		<ntig>
			<termGrp>
				<term>CIP (Classification of Instructional Programs) TAXONOMY OF DISCIPLINE DIVISIONS</term>
			</termGrp>
		</ntig>
		<descrip type="definition">taxonomy of academic disciplines which can be used to classify either courses or ACADEMIC PROGRAMS.  The taxonomy is further refined by second and third tiers of subcategories within each major division.  Designed by the Federal Department of Education, the Classification of Instructional Programs is meant to expand upon and replace the older HEGIS TAXONOMY OF DISCIPLINE DIVISIONS.  For more information and a list of current CIP codes, visit the NCES website. 
		[See also DISCIPLINE and HEGIS TAXONOMY OF DISCIPLINE DIVISIONS] </descrip>
	</langSet>
</termEntry>
<termEntry>
	<langSet xml:lang="en">
		<ntig>
			<termGrp>
				<term>CIVIC ENGAGEMENT</term>
			</termGrp>
		</ntig>
		<descrip type="definition">A teaching and learning focus on educating students as citizens. Classes or programs include meaningful civic education and activities for social good. Classes and projects have components of reflection and engagement.  This is an Applied Learning Activity.  </descrip>
	</langSet>
</termEntry>
<termEntry>
	<langSet xml:lang="en">
		<ntig>
			<termGrp>
				<term>CLINICAL PLACEMENT</term>
			</termGrp>
		</ntig>
		<descrip type="definition">Students rotate through a variety of health care agencies with faculty supervision focusing on the health care field process, with individual patients or groups reflecting diverse settings, across the lifespan. Emphasis is on mastering theoretical concepts, improving skill competency, and developing clinical reasoning skills with a focus on evidence-based practice.  This is an Applied Learning Activity. </descrip>
	</langSet>
</termEntry>
<termEntry>
	<langSet xml:lang="en">
		<ntig>
			<termGrp>
				<term>COALITION APPLICATION</term>
			</termGrp>
		</ntig>
		<descrip type="definition">The Coalition Application is a college application platform that began in July 2016 for 2017 admissions to both public and private colleges.  As of November 2022, two SUNY colleges are members (Binghamton and University at Buffalo).  Member requirements include: (1) Having a stable 70 percent six-year graduation rate 
		(2) Meeting specific affordability guidelines, as follows:  (a) Public universities “must have affordable in-state tuition for residents of their state.” (b) Private schools “must have a commitment to meet the full, demonstrated financial need of admitted domestic students.” 
		See www.coalitionforcollegeaccess.org for more information. </descrip>
	</langSet>
</termEntry>
<termEntry>
	<langSet xml:lang="en">
		<ntig>
			<termGrp>
				<term>COHORT</term>
			</termGrp>
		</ntig>
		<descrip type="definition">A group of students tracked longitudinally to assess traditional academic outcomes.  For example, an entering cohort is typically tracked to establish retention and graduation rates.  Common defining characteristics of a cohort may include FIRST-TIME or transfer status, full or part-time status, race/ethnicity, gender, entering student SAT scores or GPAs, and EOP status.   </descrip>
	</langSet>
</termEntry>
<termEntry>
	<langSet xml:lang="en">
		<ntig>
			<termGrp>
				<term>COIL Course</term>
			</termGrp>
		</ntig>
		<descrip type="definition">A COIL (Collaborative Online International Leaning) course involves collaborative international learning by connecting classes between U.S. institutions and universities around the world. The course should involve a minimum of 4 weeks of project-based interaction between SUNY and international students using online technologies (synchronous, asynchronous, or both). The content of the online exchange can be related to course material, interdisciplinary, or designed to meet specific intercultural competency goals. A COIL course should incorporate intercultural learning outcomes as well as student reflection on the experience. </descrip>
		<descrip type="example">[SIRIS TERM SECTION element SPECIAL SECTION CURRICULAR ATTRIBUTE TT210 – Code 29] </descrip>
	</langSet>
</termEntry>
<termEntry>
	<langSet xml:lang="en">
		<ntig>
			<termGrp>
				<term>COLLEGE IN THE HIGH SCHOOL</term>
			</termGrp>
		</ntig>
		<descrip type="definition">A program allowing high school students an opportunity to earn college credit by enrolling in approved college-administered/overseen courses at area high schools and taught by high school teachers.  Participating students concurrently gain both high school credit and college credit through the course. 
		For state-operated campuses, this activity is generally self-supporting and does not garner official HEADCOUNT or AAFTE unless the students are being charged the standard tuition rate charged to all other students.  These students, however, should be reported in SIRIS with ADMISSION STATUS = 11 and SPECIAL POPULATION CODE = 3 and PRIMARY ACADEMIC AWARD LEVEL=8 on the Student submission and with the appropriate course information on the Term Section submission.
		For community colleges, this activity garners official HEADCOUNT and state-supported AAFTE, regardless of whether or not the students are being charged the standard tuition rate charged to all other students.  These students should be reported on the SIRIS Student submission with ADMISSION STATUS = 5 and SPECIAL POPULATION CODE = 3 and PRIMARY ACADEMIC AWARD LEVEL=8 on the Student Submission and with the appropriate course information on the Term Section submission. 
		Note this population is a distinct subset of students CONCURRENTLY ENROLLED IN HIGH SCHOOL. Note also that this specific population of students is now a reporting category on the NYSED-2.4 Final Fall Degree-Credit Enrollment survey.  </descrip>
	</langSet>
</termEntry>
<termEntry>
	<langSet xml:lang="en">
		<ntig>
			<termGrp>
				<term>COMBINED ACADEMIC PROGRAM</term>
			</termGrp>
		</ntig>
		<descrip type="definition">A separately registered ACADEMIC PROGRAM which combines the resources of two or more programs, degree levels, or campuses to better serve student needs.  The most common example is when two pre-existing ACADEMIC PROGRAMS are combined to allow the student to earn both degrees (associated with the pre-existing programs which are being combined) in a more timely and/or efficient manner.  The end result of completion of the program is the same as if the student completed the two individual (stand-alone) degree programs, but completing the combined program affords the student greater flexibility on how that result is achieved.   
		Other examples are when two or more campuses pool resources to offer programs they might not be able to offer individually.  In such cases, work is often, but not always, required at more than one of the participating institutions to complete the degree program(s). </descrip>
	</langSet>
</termEntry>
<termEntry>
	<langSet xml:lang="en">
		<ntig>
			<termGrp>
				<term>COMMON APPLICATION</term>
			</termGrp>
		</ntig>
		<descrip type="definition">An online application accepted by more than 700 higher education institutions for entrance admission throughout and beyond the United States, including both public and private colleges, for first-year and transfer student applications.  As of November 2022, the Common App is accepted by twenty-five colleges within SUNY.  Membership requirements include: 
		(1) Not-For-Profit (2) Undergraduate degree-granting (3) Accredited by a regional accrediting association (if inside the United States) (3) A member of the Council of International Schools (if outside the United States) (4) Committed to the pursuit of equity and integrity in the college admission process. 
		See www.commonapp.org for more information. </descrip>
	</langSet>
</termEntry>
<termEntry>
	<langSet xml:lang="en">
		<ntig>
			<termGrp>
				<term>COMMUNITY SERVICE</term>
			</termGrp>
		</ntig>
		<descrip type="definition">Volunteerism and community service performed by students for community benefit. This service can be but is not necessarily integrated with a particular program of study. This may include structured projects (days of service), smaller group projects, fund-raising events, or individual volunteerism which is acknowledged by the campus.  This is an Applied Learning Activity. </descrip>
	</langSet>
</termEntry>
<termEntry>
	<langSet xml:lang="en">
		<ntig>
			<termGrp>
				<term>CONCURRENTLY ENROLLED IN HIGH SCHOOL STUDENT</term>
			</termGrp>
		</ntig>
		<descrip type="definition">A student that is simultaneously enrolled in high school and college before completing/terminating his or her high school education.  A concurrently enrolled student should be classified as a FIRST-TIME STUDENT in the fall/spring term immediately following the completion/termination of his or her high school education.  
			For state-operated institutions, only students being charged standard tuition and enrolling through the college’s normal registration process should be reported on SIRIS submissions as HOME INSTITUTION STUDENTS.   
			See COLLEGE IN THE HIGH SCHOOL for information related to the reporting of the subset of Concurrently Enrolled in High School students who are participating in College in the High School programs. </descrip>
		<descrip type="example">[See STUDENT SIRIS element SE020 HIGHER EDUCATION HISTORY] </descrip>
	</langSet>
</termEntry>
<termEntry>
	<langSet xml:lang="en">
		<ntig>
			<termGrp>
				<term>CONFLUENCE</term>
			</termGrp>
		</ntig>
		<descrip type="definition">An online environment whereby a “team collaborates and shares knowledge – creates, shares, and discusses files, ideas, minutes, specs, mockups, diagrams, and projects.”  For SIRIS purposes, this is where the latest data dictionaries, a number of appendices, FAQs, coordinator contact information, latest news items, etc. can be found. </descrip>
		<descrip type="example">Located at https://confluence.itec.suny.edu/confluence/display/cs2/Confluence+CS-DTS </descrip>
		<descrip type="example">To obtain access, an e-mail (as outlined below) can be sent to SIRISRequest@sysadm.suny.edu:  </descrip>
		<descrip type="example">Subject line:  Requesting Access to CS-DTS </descrip>
		<descrip type="example">Message body:  Please grant the following person(s) access to CD-DTS:</descrip>
		<descrip type="example">First &amp; last name </descrip>
		<descrip type="example">Existing Confluence user ID / or Campus LAN ID </descrip>
		<descrip type="example">Title </descrip>
		<descrip type="example">DTS project role (or reason for access) </descrip>
		<descrip type="example">Phone number </descrip>
		<descrip type="example">E-mail address </descrip>
	</langSet>
</termEntry>
<termEntry>
	<langSet xml:lang="en">
		<ntig>
			<termGrp>
				<term>CONTINUING EDUCATION (CE)</term>
			</termGrp>
		</ntig>
		<descrip type="definition">A widely used term but associated with very diverse meanings within the broad spectrum of post-secondary learning activities and programs.  For SUNY reporting purposes, CE 
			should be considered that subset of non-credit instruction which includes the following community service, vocational training, and adult educational activities:  (1) non-degree career training  
			(2) continuing professional education  (3) workforce training (4) formal personal enrichment courses (both on-campus and online) (5) self-directed learning (such as through Internet interest groups, clubs or personal research activities)   
			(6) experiential learning as applied to problem solving. SUNY community colleges offering REMEDIAL instruction as part of a CE program should not report these courses as CE.  
			Rather, all state-supported remedial activities taught by CE staff should be reported with a COURSE LEVEL = 7 (Remedial - Continuing Ed) on the SIRIS Course submission.  </descrip>
	</langSet>
</termEntry>
<termEntry>
	<langSet xml:lang="en">
		<ntig>
			<termGrp>
				<term>CONTINUING/RETURNING STUDENT</term>
			</termGrp>
		</ntig>
		<descrip type="definition">Undergraduate - an UNDERGRADUATE STUDENT in the current term who has previously enrolled at the reporting institution.  See FIRST-TIME STUDENT for exception regarding first-time summer and subsequent fall enrollment and the FIRST-TIME STUDENT exception if the only prior college enrollment was as HIGHER EDUCATION HISTORY=5 at the reporting institution. Graduate - a GRADUATE STUDENT in the current term who has previously attended the reporting institution as a GRADUATE STUDENT  </descrip>
		<descrip type="example">[See STUDENT element SE020 HIGHER EDUCATION HISTORY]  </descrip>
	</langSet>
</termEntry>
<termEntry>
	<langSet xml:lang="en">
		<ntig>
			<termGrp>
				<term>CONTRACT COURSES</term>
			</termGrp>
		</ntig>
		<descrip type="definition">: Contract courses for credit enrollment are unlimited as to enrollment but must meet all of the following conditions: 
		1. The instructional activity must be contracted for and paid by a third party (a corporation, state agency, union, etc.). 
		2. The enrollment in the designated course(s) or section(s) must be restricted to individuals specified in the contract through an affiliation with the third party. 
		3. All costs of the program must be charged to the contracting third party and per student rates must be set at the greater of regular tuition or at a level sufficient to cover the total costs incurred by the program, including direct instructional costs, support costs, overhead charges and fringe benefits. 
		These credit bearing activities do not generate regularly budgeted state-supported AAFTE/FTE STUDENT WORKLOAD.   </descrip>
		<descrip type="example">[See SIRIS TERM SECTION element TT140 FUNDING SOURCE] </descrip>
	</langSet>
</termEntry>
<termEntry>
	<langSet xml:lang="en">
		<ntig>
			<termGrp>
				<term>CO-OPERATIVE EDUCATION</term>
			</termGrp>
		</ntig>
	<descrip type="definition">An applied learning experience that alternates classroom learning and productive paid work experiences in a field related to a student’s academic and career goals. Co-ops are formal partnerships between an educational institution, an employer, and one or more students, and typically provide meaningful work experiences for students. Co-ops are off-campus and full-time or part-time.  This is an Applied Learning Activity. </descrip>
	</langSet>
</termEntry>
<termEntry>
	<langSet xml:lang="en">
		<ntig>
			<termGrp>
				<term>COUNTRY OF CITIZENSHIP</term>
			</termGrp>
		</ntig>
		<descrip type="definition">A student’s country of citizenship as listed in SIRIS Appendix H-3.  This element is used in determining a student’s PERMANENT RESIDENCY for enrollment reporting purposes.   
		Note that citizens of the United States cannot have a foreign VISA CODE.  If country of citizenship is anything other than the United States, a VISA CODE is required. 
		Those with dual citizenship should be reported as one or the other, at the campus’ choosing. </descrip>
		<descrip type="example">[SIRIS STUDENT element SS010] </descrip>
	</langSet>
</termEntry>
<termEntry>
	<langSet xml:lang="en">
		<ntig>
			<termGrp>
				<term>COURSE CONTENT</term>
			</termGrp>
		</ntig>
		<descrip type="definition">The 6-digit CIP CODE describing the area of knowledge of the course.  Not necessarily directly related to the department teaching the course, the degree program requiring the course, or the background of students enrolled in the course.   </descrip>
		<descrip type="example">[SIRIS COURSE element CC040] </descrip>
	</langSet>
</termEntry>
<termEntry>
	<langSet xml:lang="en">
		<ntig>
			<termGrp>
				<term>COURSE ENROLLMENT</term>
			</termGrp>
		</ntig>
		<descrip type="definition">The total number of unduplicated students, regardless of FULL-TIME or PART-TIME status, in the various SECTIONS of a course.   </descrip>
	</langSet>
</termEntry>
<termEntry>
	<langSet xml:lang="en">
		<ntig>
			<termGrp>
				<term>COURSE LEVEL</term>
			</termGrp>
		</ntig>
		<descrip type="definition">The instructional level of a course based on the level of student at which the course is primarily directed.  </descrip>
		<descrip type="example">[SIRIS COURSE element CC030] </descrip>
		<descrip type="example">SIRIS reporting codes are as follows: </descrip>
		<descrip type="example">REMEDIAL/DEVELOPMENTAL:  This code is no longer used after October 1, 2014. Remedial and Developmental courses should be reported separately using codes (7) Remedial–Continuing Ed, (8) Remedial–Non-Continuing Ed or (9) Developmental.</descrip>
		<descrip type="example">2 LOWER DIVISION </descrip>
		<descrip type="example">3 UPPER DIVISION </descrip>
		<descrip type="example">4 GRADUATE </descrip>
		<descrip type="example">5 CONTINUING EDUCATION </descrip>
		<descrip type="example">6 EOC (Educational Opportunity Center) </descrip>
		<descrip type="example">7 REMEDIAL-CONTINUING ED </descrip>
		<descrip type="example">8 REMEDIAL-NON-CONTINUING ED </descrip>
		<descrip type="example">9 DEVELOPMENTAL </descrip>
	</langSet>
</termEntry>
<termEntry>
	<langSet xml:lang="en">
		<ntig>
			<termGrp>
				<term>COURSE SUBMISSION</term>
			</termGrp>
		</ntig>
		<descrip type="definition">See SIRIS COURSE  </descrip>
	</langSet>
</termEntry>
<termEntry>
	<langSet xml:lang="en">
		<ntig>
			<termGrp>
				<term>COURSE SUBMISSION AND EVALUATION SYSTEM (CourSES)</term>
			</termGrp>
		</ntig>
		<descrip type="definition">A database maintained by the SUNY System Administration Office of Academic Programs and Planning containing courses that have been reviewed and approved as GENERAL EDUCATION COURSES or non-credit remedial courses approved for state-support.  In Spring 2021, the General Education Indicator was restored in the SIRIS Course submission.  
			Visit https://suny.edu/courses to access the CourSES database. See https://system.suny.edu/academic-affairs/acaproplan/general-education for more information.  </descrip>
	</langSet>
</termEntry>
<termEntry>
	<langSet xml:lang="en">
		<ntig>
			<termGrp>
				<term>COURSES SUPPORTED BY ACCOUNT CC2423</term>
			</termGrp>
		</ntig>
		<descrip type="definition">According to the Uniform System of Accounts for Community Colleges and the Manual for Community College Business Officers, these courses are offered on a self-sustaining basis at the request of and for the benefit of local business or non-profit organizations. These courses are also called contract courses and their costs are recorded under Account CC2423, Sponsored Research and Other Sponsored Programs-Other Programs.   </descrip>
	</langSet>
</termEntry>
<termEntry>
	<langSet xml:lang="en">
		<ntig>
			<termGrp>
				<term>CREATIVE WORKS</term>
			</termGrp>
		</ntig>
		<descrip type="definition">A capstone, senior project, performance, or other creative work that occurs as a culminating experience for a student in an accredited class or program.  This is an Applied Learning Activity. </descrip>
	</langSet>
</termEntry>
<termEntry>
	<langSet xml:lang="en">
		<ntig>
			<termGrp>
				<term>CREDIT COURSE</term>
			</termGrp>
		</ntig>
		<descrip type="definition">A course that can be used to meet the requirements of a degree, diploma, or certificate granted by the reporting institution. [See also CREDIT HOURS and CREDIT COURSE STUDENT] </descrip>
	</langSet>
</termEntry>
<termEntry>
	<langSet xml:lang="en">
		<ntig>
			<termGrp>
				<term>CREDIT COURSE STUDENT</term>
			</termGrp>
		</ntig>
		<descrip type="definition">A student enrolled in at least one CREDIT COURSE or at least one course which generates EQUIVALENT CREDIT HOURS, such as REQUIRED NON-CREDIT COURSES or NON-CREDIT COURSES for SPECIAL STUDENTS. </descrip>
	</langSet>
</termEntry>
<termEntry>
	<langSet xml:lang="en">
		<ntig>
			<termGrp>
				<term>CREDIT HOURS</term>
			</termGrp>
		</ntig>
		<descrip type="definition">The number of academic units assigned to a CREDIT COURSE.  Synonymous with credits and CREDIT VALUE. 
			Credit hours should be calculated in accordance with SUPPORTING DOCUMENT Memorandum to Presidents, Vol. 76, No. 8, &quot;Credit/Contract Hour Relationship&quot;.  In summary, the relationship between class hours and credit hours over a term is as follows: 
			(1) If the method of instruction is lecture, seminar, quiz, discussion or recitation, then one class contact hour per week per term would be awarded one credit hour. 
			(2) If the method of instruction involves activity supervised as a group such as laboratory, field trip, practicum, workshop or group studies, then three class contact hours per week per term would be awarded one credit hour unless the activity requires substantial outside preparation by the student in which case two class contact hours per week per term would be awarded one credit hour. 
			(3) In the case of supervised individual activity, such as independent study, individual studio and tutorial, calculate credit hours as follows:  
				(a) for independent study defined as study given initial guidance, criticism, review and evaluation by a faculty member, the equivalent of three student academic activity hours per week per term would be awarded one credit hour;  
				(b) for tutorial study defined as study which is given initial faculty guidance followed by repeated, regularly scheduled individual student conferences with a faculty member and periodic as well as final evaluation one instructional contact hour per week per term would be awarded one credit hour. 
			(4) If the student is engaged in independent activity which is essentially full-time, as in the case of student teaching, then each week of work would be the equivalent of one credit hour. 
			See EQUIVALENT CREDIT HOURS for non-credit instructional activities which generate state-aidable FULL-TIME EQUIVALENT WORKLOAD.   </descrip>
	</langSet>
</termEntry>
<termEntry>
	<langSet xml:lang="en">
		<ntig>
			<termGrp>
				<term>CREDIT VALUE</term>
			</termGrp>
		</ntig>
		<descrip type="definition">See CREDIT HOURS</descrip>
	</langSet>
</termEntry>
<termEntry>
	<langSet xml:lang="en">
		<ntig>
			<termGrp>
				<term>CREDITS ATTEMPTED</term>
			</termGrp>
		</ntig>
		<descrip type="definition">The number of CREDIT HOURS the student would earn upon successful completion of the course.  For a REMEDIAL COURSE, a DEVELOPMENTAL COURSE, or a REQUIRED NON-CREDIT COURSE, this would be the EQUIVALENT (IMPUTED) CREDIT HOURS. </descrip>
		<descrip type="example">[SIRIS TERM SECTION element TE050]  </descrip>
	</langSet>
</termEntry>
<termEntry>
	<langSet xml:lang="en">
		<ntig>
			<termGrp>
				<term>CREDITS EARNED</term>
			</termGrp>
		</ntig>
		<descrip type="definition">The actual number of CREDIT HOURS earned by the student upon completion of the course. </descrip>
		<descrip type="example">[SIRIS TERM SECTION element TE060] </descrip>
	</langSet>
</termEntry>
<termEntry>
	<langSet xml:lang="en">
		<ntig>
			<termGrp>
				<term>CROSS REGISTRATION</term>
			</termGrp>
		</ntig>
		<descrip type="definition">A cooperative arrangement between colleges that allows a student to receive instruction and obtain academic credit for courses administered by an institution other than the student’s home institution.  These arrangements are to be established on a quid pro quo basis.   
			The college will receive FTE WORKLOAD for teaching cross-registered students from another college, but will not receive FTE WORKLOAD for the instruction given to their students by another college.  A cross-registered student will count in the official HEADCOUNT enrollment at his or her HOME INSTITUTION only. </descrip>
	</langSet>
</termEntry>
<termEntry>
	<langSet xml:lang="en">
		<ntig>
			<termGrp>
				<term>CROSS-LISTED</term>
			</termGrp>
		</ntig>
		<descrip type="definition">:  See EQUIVALENT COURSE and SIMULTANEOUS USAGE </descrip>
	</langSet>
</termEntry>
<termEntry>
	<langSet xml:lang="en">
		<ntig>
			<termGrp>
				<term>CUMULATIVE GRADE POINT AVERAGE (GPA)</term>
			</termGrp>
		</ntig>
		<descrip type="definition">A student’s cumulative grade point average, on a 4-point scale, as of the beginning of the current term.  Must be calculated in a manner consistent with New York State Education Department (NYSED) guidelines. </descrip>
		<descrip type="example">[SIRIS STUDENT element SE130]  </descrip>
	</langSet>
</termEntry>
<termEntry>
	<langSet xml:lang="en">
		<ntig>
			<termGrp>
				<term>DATE OF BIRTH</term>
			</termGrp>
		</ntig>
		<descrip type="definition">Student's date of birth in MMDDYYYY format.  For SUNY ID assignment, required if a student’s SSN has not been reported.  Used for SIRIS matching purposes. </descrip>
		<descrip type="example">[SIRIS STUDENT element SD060, SIRIS DEGREE element DS050]  </descrip>
	</langSet>
</termEntry>
<termEntry>
	<langSet xml:lang="en">
		<ntig>
			<termGrp>
				<term>DEGREE SUBMISSION</term>
			</termGrp>
		</ntig>
		<descrip type="definition">See SIRIS DEGREE  </descrip>
	</langSet>
</termEntry>
<termEntry>
	<langSet xml:lang="en">
		<ntig>
			<termGrp>
				<term>DEGREE WORKS</term>
			</termGrp>
		</ntig>
		<descrip type="definition">Delivered by Ellucian, Degree Works is a comprehensive academic advising and degree audit solution that helps students and their advisors successfully negotiate curriculum requirements.  SUNY has invested in a customized version of the software for use system-wide that includes ‘transfer finder’, allowing students to search for programs at other SUNY institutions and perform degree audits against any program that is available in the central program database. </descrip>
	</langSet>
</termEntry>
<termEntry>
	<langSet xml:lang="en">
		<ntig>
			<termGrp>
				<term>DEGREE/CERTIFICATE AWARD DATE</term>
			</termGrp>
		</ntig>
		<descrip type="definition">The date on which a degree/certificate is officially awarded, the date which appears on the student’s degree, certificate, or diploma. </descrip>
		<descrip type="example">[SIRIS DEGREE element DD060] </descrip>
	</langSet>
</termEntry>
<termEntry>
	<langSet xml:lang="en">
		<ntig>
			<termGrp>
				<term>DEVELOPMENTAL COURSE</term>
			</termGrp>
		</ntig>
		<descrip type="definition">A developmental course combines pre-college and college level material and results in some credit awarded toward a degree. It is designed for students deficient in the general competencies necessary for a regular postsecondary curriculum.  At the beginning of the course, the content is at the pre-college level, but by the end of the course, the content is at the college level.  The portion of the course at the pre-college level generates equivalent credit hours, and the portion at the college level generates actual degree-satisfying credit hours. </descrip>
</langSet>
</termEntry>
<termEntry>
	<langSet xml:lang="en">
		<ntig>
			<termGrp>
				<term>DISABLED</term>
			</termGrp>
		</ntig>
		<descrip type="definition">A student with a physical or mental impairment that substantially limits one or more of the major life activities of such an individual; and with a record of such impairment; or being regarded as having such an impairment. 
		[See also STUDENTS WITH DISABILITIES] </descrip>
</langSet>
</termEntry>
<termEntry>
	<langSet xml:lang="en">
		<ntig>
			<termGrp>
				<term>DISADVANTAGED STUDENT</term>
			</termGrp>
		</ntig>
		<descrip type="definition">A student who is eligible for supplemental financial assistance in Education Opportunity Programs under criteria established by the State University of New York, pursuant to section 6452 of the Education Law and Subpart 27¬2 of Part 27 of Chapter I of Title 8 of the Official Compilation of Codes, Rules and Regulations of the State of New York (Rules of the Board of Regents).  This definition applies irrespective of whether or not the institution has such an Education Opportunity Program or whether or not the individual is receiving such funds.   
			[See SUPPORTING DOCUMENT “EOP Eligibility”]  </descrip>
</langSet>
</termEntry>
<termEntry>
	<langSet xml:lang="en">
		<ntig>
			<termGrp>
				<term>DISPLACED HOMEMAKER</term>
			</termGrp>
		</ntig>
		<descrip type="definition"> A student who a) has worked primarily without remuneration to care for a home and family and for that reason, has diminished marketable skills; or b) has been dependent on the income of another family member but is no longer supported by such income; or c) is a parent whose youngest dependent child will become eligible to receive assistance under Part A of Title V of the Social Security Act not later than two years after the date on which the parent applies for assistance under this title; and is unemployed or underemployed and is experiencing difficulty in obtaining or upgrading employment. </descrip>
</langSet>
</termEntry>
<termEntry>
	<langSet xml:lang="en">
		<ntig>
			<termGrp>
				<term>DOUBLE MAJOR</term>
			</termGrp>
		</ntig>
		<descrip type="definition">When a student earns what the institution considers one degree but satisfies the requirements of two (or more) different ACADEMIC PROGRAMS (majors).  Either major could legally be considered the degree of record in such cases.  Typically, but not exclusively, happens at the baccalaureate level.  It occurs when the credits earned in pursuit of the two sets of requirements do not result in sufficient extra work (beyond 120 credits, for example, in the case of a bachelor’s degree) for the institution granting the degree to consider the result two separate and distinct degrees.   
		[See SUPPORTING DOCUMENT Memorandum to Presidents Vol. 80 No. 5, Guidelines on Awarding of Two Degrees at the Same Level.] </descrip>
</langSet>
</termEntry>
<termEntry>
	<langSet xml:lang="en">
		<ntig>
			<termGrp>
				<term>DTS (DATA TRANSFER SYSTEM)</term>
			</termGrp>
		</ntig>
		<descrip type="definition">The software that allows for the online transmission, viewing, and locking of SUNY SIRIS submissions.  Only the latest submission (for each submission type – Early Student, EOT Student, Term Section, etc.) is held in the DTS environment. </descrip>
</langSet>
</termEntry>
<termEntry>
	<langSet xml:lang="en">
		<ntig>
			<termGrp>
				<term>ECONOMICALLY DISADVANTAGED</term>
			</termGrp>
		</ntig>
		<descrip type="definition">Refers to a student who participates in any of the following economic assistance programs: Pell Grant, Tuition Assistance Program (TAP), Aid for Part-Time Study (APTS), Educational Opportunity Program (EOP); Higher Education Opportunity Program (HEOP), Search for Education, Elevation and Knowledge (SEEK), and College Discovery (CD), Bureau of Indian Affairs Higher Education Grant Program (BIA), Temporary Assistance for Needy Families (TANF), Workforce Investment Act (WIA), Women, Infants and Children (WIC), other public assistance programs serving economically disadvantaged such as: Food Stamps, Home Energy Assistance Payments (HEAP), Supplemental Security Income, Trade Readjustment Act, and Refugee and Immigration Affairs Assistance. 
		For reporting purposes using SIRIS data, Student submission element SE140 Pell Grant Recipient Indicator = Yes is typically used as a proxy for identifying economically disadvantaged students.   </descrip>
</langSet>
</termEntry>
<termEntry>
	<langSet xml:lang="en">
		<ntig>
			<termGrp>
				<term>EDUCATIONAL OUTCOMES (EO) REPORTS</term>
			</termGrp>
		</ntig>
		<descrip type="definition">The EO reports array the traditional educational outcomes of GRADUATION, RETENTION/PERSISTENCE, transfer, and attrition for a COHORT of students at a specified reporting date.  The report includes outcomes beyond the institution of initial enrollment (i.e. other SUNY and non-SUNY institutions).  Outcome categories are mutually exclusive using an established hierarchy of graduation, then retention/persistence, and then transfer.   
			Typically, EO data is generated for cohorts of full-time first-time students, full-time transfer students, and entering EOP students for specified time periods, usually six years for baccalaureate cohorts and three years for associate students.   </descrip>
</langSet>
</termEntry>
<termEntry>
	<langSet xml:lang="en">
		<ntig>
			<termGrp>
				<term>ENTREPRENEURSHIP</term>
			</termGrp>
		</ntig>
		<descrip type="definition">Students in an entrepreneurship program develop a broad-based entrepreneurial skill relevant to any organization - start-up, established, and for- and not-for profit – in an industry.  Entrepreneurship involves consistently thinking and acting in ways designed to uncover new opportunities that are then applied to provide value.  This is an Applied Learning Activity. </descrip>
</langSet>
</termEntry>
<termEntry>
	<langSet xml:lang="en">
		<ntig>
			<termGrp>
				<term>EOP STUDENT, ACTIVE</term>
			</termGrp>
		</ntig>
		<descrip type="definition">An undergraduate degree-seeking student admitted into an academic program based on the requirements of the Educational Opportunity Program (EOP) who is receiving direct aid and/or services from the EOP program during the current reporting term;  
			[See also SIRIS STUDENT element SE010 ADMISSION STATUS, glossary term SPECIAL STUDENT, and SUPPORTING DOCUMENT “EOP Eligibility”]   </descrip>
</langSet>
</termEntry>
<termEntry>
	<langSet xml:lang="en">
		<ntig>
			<termGrp>
				<term>EOP STUDENT, INACTIVE</term>
			</termGrp>
		</ntig>
		<descrip type="definition">An undergraduate degree-seeking student admitted into an academic program based on the requirements of the Educational Opportunity Program (EOP) who previously received direct aid and/or services but is not receiving them during the current reporting term.  </descrip>
</langSet>
</termEntry>
<termEntry>
	<langSet xml:lang="en">
		<ntig>
			<termGrp>
				<term>EQUIVALENT COURSE</term>
			</termGrp>
		</ntig>
		<descrip type="definition">A course offered by multiple departments that may have different course titles or course IDs but have exactly the same course content and requirements.  Synonymous with CROSS-LISTED. 
			[See SIRIS COURSE element CE010 Equivalent Campus Course ID] </descrip>
</langSet>
</termEntry>
<termEntry>
	<langSet xml:lang="en">
		<ntig>
			<termGrp>
				<term>EQUIVALENT CREDIT HOURS</term>
			</termGrp>
		</ntig>
		<descrip type="definition">Imputed CREDIT HOURS used for workload calculations for certain instructional activities which generate FTE WORKLOAD but do not generate academic credits.  At both State Operated/Funded campuses and Community Colleges, this would include  
			(1) REQUIRED NON-CREDIT COURSES, such as physical education, musical ensemble, theater stagecraft, etc.  
				and  
			(2) non-credit REMEDIAL or DEVELOPMENTAL courses, such as NON-CREDIT COURSES FOR SPECIAL STUDENTS.   
			Equivalent credit hours are to be calculated in accordance with SUPPORTING DOCUMENT Memorandum to Presidents, Vol. 91, No. 2, &quot;Credit Equivalency for Non-Credit Instruction&quot;.  In summary form, the relationship between class hours and equivalent credit hours is as follows: 
			(1) Educational activities structured as typical classroom courses (including developmental and remedial courses) would be accounted for on a standard one for one basis, i. e. one class contact hour per week per term is awarded one credit hour. 
			(2) A laboratory component, typically related to a lecture, is counted on a three for one basis, i. e. three class contact hours per week per term are awarded one credit hour. 
			(3) Learning Centers, available for the individualized instruction of the student under the supervision of instructional employees, are counted on a two for one basis, i. e. two class contact hours per week per term are awarded one credit hour. 
			(4) Practice Centers, available for the casual use of the student on an as-needed basis, do not generate any equivalent credit hours. 
			See SUPPORTING DOCUMENT Memorandum to Presidents, Vol. 91, No. 2, “Credit Equivalency for Non-Credit Instruction”, for more detailed information. </descrip>
</langSet>
</termEntry>
<termEntry>
	<langSet xml:lang="en">
		<ntig>
			<termGrp>
				<term>EXCELSIOR SCHOLARSHIP</term>
			</termGrp>
		</ntig>
		<descrip type="definition">The Excelsior Scholarship provides tuition awards to income-eligible students attending New York State's public colleges and universities (i.e. SUNY and CUNY). This “last dollar” scholarship, in combination with other student financial aid programs, is intended to allow more students to attend a SUNY or CUNY college tuition-free. 
			Visit www.hesc.ny.gov/excelsior to learn more about the eligibility requirements. </descrip>
		<descrip type="example">[See SIRIS STUDENT element SE145 Excelsior Scholarship Preliminary Indicator and SIRIS FINANCIAL AID APPENDIX T Code-013 NYS Excelsior Scholarship] </descrip>
</langSet>
</termEntry>
<termEntry>
	<langSet xml:lang="en">
		<ntig>
			<termGrp>
				<term>EXCHANGE PROGRAMS</term>
			</termGrp>
		</ntig>
		<descrip type="definition">Those OVERSEAS ACADEMIC PROGRAMS (OAPs) that have been approved by System Administration in which a SUNY institution and a foreign institution agree to &quot;swap&quot; students with no net change in the overall institutional workload.   
			The workload of the SUNY students going abroad is generally considered self-supported and is excluded from FTE.  The workload of the exchange students studying at the reporting institution is considered state supported and is included in FTE.   
			The SUNY students studying abroad count in the campus’ official HEADCOUNT while the exchange students from abroad do not. </descrip>
</langSet>
</termEntry>
<termEntry>
	<langSet xml:lang="en">
		<ntig>
			<termGrp>
				<term>EXCHANGE STUDENT</term>
			</termGrp>
		</ntig>
		<descrip type="definition">A student enrolled at an international college coming to SUNY to participate in one of SUNY’s approved overseas EXCHANGE PROGRAMS.  </descrip>
		<descrip type="example">[See SIRIS STUDENT element SE010 ADMISSION STATUS] </descrip>
	</langSet>
</termEntry>
<termEntry>
	<langSet xml:lang="en">
		<ntig>
			<termGrp>
				<term>EXPERIENTIAL EDUCATION</term>
			</termGrp>
		</ntig>
		<descrip type="definition">See the specific types – CLINICAL, COMMUNITY SERVICE, CO-OPERATIVE EDUCATION, ENTREPRENEURSHIP, INTERNSHIP, RESEARCH/FIELD STUDY, and SERVICE LEARNING. </descrip>
</langSet>
</termEntry>
<termEntry>
	<langSet xml:lang="en">
		<ntig>
			<termGrp>
				<term>FACULTY CONTACT HOURS</term>
			</termGrp>
		</ntig>
		<descrip type="definition">The total hours spent by a faculty member in direct contact with students, as reflected in the scheduled instruction time for the section.  Fifty minutes of instruction equals one faculty contact hour.  Preparation time and office hours are NOT to be included.  For example, in a standard 15-week semester, a typical 3-credit lecture yields 45 faculty contact hours.  Courses with minimal faculty-student contact, such as independent study, internship, and advanced graduate research, typically yield 0 faculty contact hours. </descrip>
		<descrip type="example">[SIRIS TERM SECTION element TT110] </descrip>
		<descrip type="example">[See also SIRIS TERM SECTION elements TT090 INSTRUCTION TYPE and TT100 CREDIT/CONTACT HOUR RELATIONSHIP] </descrip>
</langSet>
</termEntry>
<termEntry>
	<langSet xml:lang="en">
		<ntig>
			<termGrp>
				<term>FAST FACTS</term>
			</termGrp>
		</ntig>
		<descrip type="definition">See SUNY FAST FACTS </descrip>
</langSet>
</termEntry>
<termEntry>
	<langSet xml:lang="en">
		<ntig>
			<termGrp>
				<term>FERPA</term>
			</termGrp>
		</ntig>
		<descrip type="definition">:  From the US Department of Education (https://www2.ed.gov/policy/gen/guid/fpco/ferpa/index.html): 
		“The Family Educational Rights and Privacy Act (FERPA) (20 U.S.C. § 1232g; 34 CFR Part 99) is a Federal law that protects the privacy of student education records. The law applies to all schools that receive funds under an applicable program of the U.S. Department of Education. 
		FERPA gives parents certain rights with respect to their children's education records. These rights transfer to the student when he or she reaches the age of 18 or attends a school beyond the high school level.  
		Students to whom the rights have transferred are "eligible students." 
		- Parents or eligible students have the right to inspect and review the student's education records maintained by the school. Schools are not required to provide copies of records unless, for reasons such as great distance, it is impossible for parents or eligible students to review the records. Schools may charge a fee for copies. 
		- Parents or eligible students have the right to request that a school correct records which they believe to be inaccurate or misleading. If the school decides not to amend the record, the parent or eligible student then has the right to a formal hearing. After the hearing, if the school still decides not to amend the record, the parent or eligible student has the right to place a statement with the record setting forth his or her view about the contested information. • Generally, schools must have written permission from the parent or eligible student in order to release any information from a student's education record. However, FERPA allows schools to disclose those records, without consent, to the following parties or under the following conditions (34 CFR § 99.31): Schools may disclose, without consent, "directory" information such as a student's name, address, telephone number, date and place of birth, honors and awards, and dates of attendance. However, schools must tell parents and eligible students about directory information and allow parents and eligible students a reasonable amount of time to request that the school not disclose directory information about them. Schools must notify parents and eligible students annually of their rights under FERPA. The actual means of notification (special letter, inclusion in a PTA bulletin, student handbook, or newspaper article) is left to the discretion of each school.” 
		See https://familypolicy.ed.gov/faq-page?src=ferpa for Frequently Asked Questions, including those specific to Postsecondary Education School Officials. </descrip>
</langSet>
</termEntry>
<termEntry>
	<langSet xml:lang="en">
		<ntig>
			<termGrp>
				<term>FIELD STUDY</term>
			</termGrp>
		</ntig>
		<descrip type="definition">Collection of information outside of an experimental or lab setting. This type of data collection is most often conducted in natural settings or environments and can be designed in a variety of ways for various disciplines. May be mentored, self-directed work, or comprise a full course. The projects include inquiry, design, investigation, discovery, and application.  This is an Applied Learning Activity. </descrip>
</langSet>
</termEntry>
<termEntry>
	<langSet xml:lang="en">
		<ntig>
			<termGrp>
				<term>FINAL GRADE POINT AVERAGE</term>
			</termGrp>
		</ntig>
		<descrip type="definition">The final grade point average, on a 4-point scale, at the time a degree/certificate is awarded. </descrip>
		<descrip type="example">[SIRIS DEGREE element DD050] </descrip>
</langSet>
</termEntry>
<termEntry>
	<langSet xml:lang="en">
		<ntig>
			<termGrp>
				<term>FINANCIAL AID SUBMISSION</term>
			</termGrp>
		</ntig>
		<descrip type="definition">:  See SIRIS FINANCIAL AID </descrip>
</langSet>
</termEntry>
<termEntry>
	<langSet xml:lang="en">
		<ntig>
			<termGrp>
				<term>FIRST GENERATION COLLEGE STUDENT</term>
			</termGrp>
		</ntig>
		<descrip type="definition">A student whose parents do not have a college degree.   </descrip>
</langSet>
</termEntry>
<termEntry>
	<langSet xml:lang="en">
		<ntig>
			<termGrp>
				<term>FIRST PROFESSIONAL</term>
			</termGrp>
		</ntig>
		<descrip type="definition">A classification that includes JD (Law) students as well as all HEALTH FIRST PROFESSIONAL students (AuD (Audiology), DDS (Dentistry), DNP (Nursing Practice), DPT (Physical Therapy), DVM (Vet Med), MD (Medical), PharmD (Pharmacy), and OD (Optometry)).   </descrip>
		<descrip type="example">[The identification of first professional students is derived from SIRIS STUDENT element SE030 ACADEMIC PROGRAM - PRIMARY.] </descrip>
</langSet>
</termEntry>
<termEntry>
	<langSet xml:lang="en">
		<ntig>
			<termGrp>
				<term>FIRST-TIME STUDENT</term>
			</termGrp>
		</ntig>
		<descrip type="definition">A student who has not attended any college or university after completing/terminating his or her high school education and is enrolling at the reporting institution for the first time in the current term.   
			Students simultaneously enrolled in high school and college should be classified as CONCURRENTLY ENROLLED IN HIGH SCHOOL.  A student whose previous post-secondary education was only at a non-collegiate institution such as a business school or technical institute is a FIRST-TIME STUDENT, unless the institution expects to award college credit for such activities, in which case the student is a TRANSFER STUDENT.   
			A student who has completed/terminated his or her high school education and is enrolled at the college for the first time during the summer term should be reported as unknown for the summer term and then reported as FIRST-TIME STUDENT for the immediate following fall term.   
			A student who has not attended any college or university after completing/terminating his or her high school education and their only prior college enrollment at the reporting institution was as HIGHER EDUCATION HISTORY=5 should be reported as a FIRST-TIME STUDENT. </descrip>
		<descrip type="example">[See SIRIS STUDENT element SE020 HIGHER EDUCATION HISTORY]   </descrip>
</langSet>
</termEntry>
<termEntry>
	<langSet xml:lang="en">
		<ntig>
			<termGrp>
				<term>FOREIGN STUDENT</term>
			</termGrp>
		</ntig>
		<descrip type="definition">An international student who is neither a citizen of the United States nor holds Legal Permanent Residence status.  Students recognized as UNDOCUMENTED ALIENS are not considered foreign students. </descrip>
		<descrip type="example">[See SIRIS STUDENT elements SS010 COUNTRY OF CITIZENSHIP and SS020 VISA CODE]  </descrip>
</langSet>
</termEntry>
<termEntry>
	<langSet xml:lang="en">
		<ntig>
			<termGrp>
				<term>FORMER INSTITUTION</term>
			</termGrp>
		</ntig>
		<descrip type="definition">For UNDERGRADUATE TRANSFER STUDENTS, the most relevant post-secondary institution attended by a student prior to enrollment at the reporting institution.    
			For GRADUATE STUDENTS, the institution which granted the bachelor’s degree.   
			For US institutions, either the IPEDS Unit ID or the College Board CEEB Code can be submitted on SIRIS. </descrip>
		<descrip type="example">[See SIRIS STUDENT elements SP030 Former Institution – UnitID and SP035 Former Institution – CEEB]  </descrip>
</langSet>
</termEntry>
<termEntry>
	<langSet xml:lang="en">
		<ntig>
			<termGrp>
				<term>FRESHMAN</term>
			</termGrp>
		</ntig>
		<descrip type="definition">A STUDENT LEVEL derived as follows: 
		A student MATRICULATED in a PROGRAM who has accumulated fewer than 30 CREDIT HOURS.  
		All students in diploma or certificate programs of one year or less are considered freshmen.</descrip>
		<descrip type="example">[See SIRIS STUDENT elements SE030 ACADEMIC PROGRAM – PRIMARY and SE110 ACCUMULATED CREDIT HOURS]  </descrip>
</langSet>
</termEntry>
<termEntry>
	<langSet xml:lang="en">
		<ntig>
			<termGrp>
				<term>FULL-TIME EQUIVALENT (FTE) FACULTY</term>
			</termGrp>
		</ntig>
		<descrip type="definition">Like full-time equivalent workload, FTE faculty is a unit of measure to equate faculty appointments of various fractions of full-time status to full-time appointments. Full-time faculty equal one FTE.  Part-time faculty appointment fractions are accumulated to an equivalency of full-time appointments.  The full-time or part-time status of faculty is generally defined by contract and for purposes here is extracted from appropriate personnel records.  Special procedures exist for imputing an FTE for temporary service faculty, contributed service staff, etc.    </descrip>
</langSet>
</termEntry>
<termEntry>
	<langSet xml:lang="en">
		<ntig>
			<termGrp>
				<term>FULL-TIME EQUIVALENT (FTE) STUDENT WORKLOAD</term>
			</termGrp>
		</ntig>
		<descrip type="definition">A unit of measure applicable to a semester and typically derived from student CREDIT HOURS.  SUNY obtains these student credit hours from the SIRIS TERM SECTION submission.   
			Generally speaking, one FTE workload is equivalent to 15 student credit hours in undergraduate courses or 12 student credit hours in graduate courses.  Health first-professional and advanced graduate student FTEs are based on headcount and calculated as follows:  one FTE for first professionals in the health sciences, one FTE for full-time ADVANCED GRADUATE STUDENTS, and 0.75 FTE for part-time ADVANCED GRADUATE STUDENTS.   </descrip>
</langSet>
</termEntry>
<termEntry>
	<langSet xml:lang="en">
		<ntig>
			<termGrp>
				<term>FULL-TIME STUDENT</term>
			</termGrp>
		</ntig>
		<descrip type="definition">For headcount reporting purposes, 
			Full-time undergraduate - an UNDERGRADUATE STUDENT who is enrolled for 12 or more CREDIT HOURS 
			Full-time graduate - a GRADUATE STUDENT who is enrolled for 9 or more CREDIT HOURS 
			For tuition purposes, 
			Full-time undergraduate - an UNDERGRADUATE STUDENT who is enrolled for 12 or more CREDIT HOURS 
			Full-time graduate - a GRADUATE STUDENT who is enrolled for 12 or more CREDIT HOURS 
			In determining full-time status, EQUIVALENT CREDIT HOURS imputed to non-credit courses are included in addition to those credit hours in standard credit courses.  See also glossary entries CREDIT COURSE, REQUIRED NON-CREDIT COURSE, NONCREDIT COURSES FOR SPECIAL STUDENTS, CREDIT HOURS, and EQUIVALENT CREDIT HOURS.  </descrip>
		<descrip type="example">The identification of students as full- or part-time is derived from SIRIS STUDENT elements SE020 HIGHER EDUCATION HISTORY and SE070 TOTAL CREDIT HOURS.  Official counts come from the SIRIS Early Student submission. </descrip>
</langSet>
</termEntry>
<termEntry>
	<langSet xml:lang="en">
		<ntig>
			<termGrp>
				<term>FUNDING SOURCE</term>
			</termGrp>
		</ntig>
		<descrip type="definition">:  The source of funding for a given course SECTION. </descrip>
		<descrip type="example">[SIRIS TERM SECTION element TT140] </descrip>
		<descrip type="example">SIRIS reporting codes are as follows: </descrip>
		<descrip type="example">1  State supported </descrip>
		<descrip type="example">2  Self supported by tuition </descrip>
		<descrip type="example">3  Contract course </descrip>
		<descrip type="example">4  Self supported by fee </descrip>
		<descrip type="example">5  State supported with associated fee </descrip>
		<descrip type="example">6  Self supported with associated fee </descrip>
</langSet>
</termEntry>
<termEntry>
	<langSet xml:lang="en">
		<ntig>
			<termGrp>
				<term>GENDER</term>
			</termGrp>
		</ntig>
		<descrip type="definition">See Sex. </descrip>
</langSet>
</termEntry>
<termEntry>
	<langSet xml:lang="en">
		<ntig>
			<termGrp>
				<term>GENDER IDENTITY</term>
			</termGrp>
		</ntig>
		<descrip type="definition">The gender the student self-identifies with.  One’s gender identity can be the same as or different than their SEX.  (SEX is a data element that was formerly named Gender in this glossary and in SIRIS). </descrip>
		<descrip type="example">[SIRIS STUDENT element SD075] </descrip>
		<descrip type="example">SIRIS reporting codes are as follows: </descrip>
		<descrip type="example">M  Male </descrip>
		<descrip type="example">F    Female </descrip>
		<descrip type="example">X   Non-binary </descrip>
		<descrip type="example">U   Unknown </descrip>
</langSet>
</termEntry>
<termEntry>
	<langSet xml:lang="en">
		<ntig>
			<termGrp>
				<term>GENERAL EDUCATION COURSE</term>
			</termGrp>
		</ntig>
		<descrip type="definition"> course that has received System Administration approval for meeting SUNY general education requirements through the Course Submission and Evaluation System (CourSES) - https://suny.edu/courses - for approval.   See https://system.suny.edu/academic-affairs/acaproplan/general-education for more information.  
		In Spring 2021, the General Education Indicator was restored in SIRIS course submission. </descrip>
		<descrip type="example">[SIRIS COURSE element CC090 General Education Indicator] </descrip>
</langSet>
</termEntry>
<termEntry>
	<langSet xml:lang="en">
		<ntig>
			<termGrp>
				<term>GLOBAL SUNY ID</term>
			</termGrp>
		</ntig>
		<descrip type="definition">A unique identifier assigned by SUNY System Administration to SUNY students and employees.   Global SUNY ID replaces SUNY Student ID and SUNY Employee ID.  Prior to implementing Global SUNY ID, a person could have a SUNY Student ID, a SUNY Employee ID, or both assigned to them depending on how they were affiliated with the SUNY System.  The move to a single ID, Global SUNY ID, was initiated to streamline processes and improve efficiencies in managing them.  Global SUNY ID was requirement for implementing and participating in Ellucian’s Degree Works and the SUNY Digital Learning Environment. 
			In August 2021, all students and employees were assigned a unique Global SUNY ID.  For individuals with one SUNY ID (either Student’s SUNY ID or Employee ID), Global SUNY ID is the same as the existing ID.  For individuals with both a Student SUNY ID and an Employee SUNY ID, the existing Employee ID was assigned as their Global SUNY ID.  
			In order to assign a Global SUNY ID, the following data elements are required: 
			- Local ID 
			- Date of Birth (required if SSN is not reported) 
			- Gender 
			- Last Name (required if first name is blank) 
			- First Name (required if last name is blank) 
			See SIRIS Appendix P for more details. </descrip>
		<descrip type="example">[SIRIS STUDENT element SD040, SIRIS DEGREE element DS025, SIRIS TERM SECTION element TF030, SIRIS TERM SECTION element TE020 for Students and TF030 for instructors] </descrip>
</langSet>
</termEntry>
<termEntry>
	<langSet xml:lang="en">
		<ntig>
			<termGrp>
				<term>GRADE POINT AVERAGE (GPA)</term>
			</termGrp>
		</ntig>
		<descrip type="definition">See CUMULATIVE GRADE POINT AVERAGE </descrip>
</langSet>
</termEntry>
<termEntry>
	<langSet xml:lang="en">
		<ntig>
			<termGrp>
				<term>GRADUATE LEVEL COURSE</term>
			</termGrp>
		</ntig>
		<descrip type="definition">A course directed primarily at GRADUATE STUDENTS.</descrip>
	</langSet>
</termEntry>
<termEntry>
	<langSet xml:lang="en">
		<ntig>
			<termGrp>
				<term>GRADUATE STUDENT</term>
			</termGrp>
		</ntig>
		<descrip type="definition">A student who is  
			(1) in a graduate program (or the graduation portion of a COMBINED ACADEMIC PROGRAM) 
			OR 
			(2) not in a graduate program but has been accepted by the reporting institution for graduate study in the current term  
			OR 
			(3) not in a graduate program but holds a bachelor's degree and is enrolled in at least one graduate level credit course for post-graduate credit. 
			[See STUDENT LEVEL] </descrip>
</langSet>
</termEntry>
<termEntry>
	<langSet xml:lang="en">
		<ntig>
			<termGrp>
				<term>GRADUATE STUDENT (NOT IN A PROGRAM)</term>
			</termGrp>
		</ntig>
		<descrip type="definition">:  A student who is  
			(1)  not in a graduate program but has been accepted by the reporting institution for graduate study in the current term  
			OR  
			(2)  not in a graduate program but holds a bachelor's degree and is enrolled in at least one graduate level credit course for post-graduate credit. </descrip>
</langSet>
</termEntry>
<termEntry>
	<langSet xml:lang="en">
		<ntig>
			<termGrp>
				<term>GRADUATION RATE</term>
			</termGrp>
		</ntig>
		<descrip type="definition">The percentage of students from an entering COHORT who graduate within a specific time frame at the reporting institution.  For example, a first-time, full-time COHORT of STUDENTS IN A BACHELOR’S DEGREE PROGRAM would typically be assessed at 4, 5, and 6 years out.  Similarly, STUDENTS IN AN ASSOCIATE’S DEGREE PROGRAM would typically be assessed at 2, 3, and 4 years out.   
		[See also STUDENT RIGHT-TO-KNOW]  </descrip>
</langSet>
</termEntry>
<termEntry>
	<langSet xml:lang="en">
		<ntig>
			<termGrp>
				<term>GRADWAGES</term>
			</termGrp>
		</ntig>
		<descrip type="definition">See SUNY GRADWAGES </descrip>
</langSet>
</termEntry>
<termEntry>
	<langSet xml:lang="en">
		<ntig>
			<termGrp>
				<term>HEADCOUNT (STUDENT)</term>
			</termGrp>
		</ntig>
		<descrip type="definition">For purposes of official headcount enrollment reporting, the number of students enrolled in one or more courses on or after the course’s CENSUS DATE, with each student counted only once.  This number is not to be a count of class registrations.   
		Official headcounts come from the SIRIS Early Student submission. </descrip>
</langSet>
</termEntry>
<termEntry>
	<langSet xml:lang="en">
		<ntig>
			<termGrp>
				<term>HEALTH FIRST PROFESSIONAL</term>
			</termGrp>
		</ntig>
		<descrip type="definition">A derived STUDENT LEVEL defined as follows: 
			A student in a program leading to one of the following degrees in the health sciences:  AuD (Audiology), DDS (Dentistry), DNP (Nursing Practice), DPT (Physical Therapy), DVM (Vet Med), MD (Medical), PharmD (Pharmacy), OD (Optometry), and OTD (Occupational Therapy).   </descrip>
		<descrip type="example">[The identification of health first professional students is derived from SIRIS STUDENT element SE030 ACADEMIC PROGRAM - PRIMARY.] </descrip>
</langSet>
</termEntry>
<termEntry>
	<langSet xml:lang="en">
		<ntig>
			<termGrp>
				<term>HEGIS (Higher Education General Information System) TAXONOMY OF DISCIPLINE DIVISIONS</term>
			</termGrp>
		</ntig>
		<descrip type="definition">taxonomy of 30 academic disciplines which NYS uses to classify ACADEMIC PROGRAMS.  For a complete listing of the HEGIS taxonomy, see the SUPPORTING DOCUMENTS.   
			For other uses, HEGIS has been replaced by CIP (Classification of Instructional Programs).   
			[See also CIP TAXONOMY OF DISCIPLINE DIVISIONS]  </descrip>
</langSet>
</termEntry>
<termEntry>
	<langSet xml:lang="en">
		<ntig>
			<termGrp>
				<term>HIGH NEEDS</term>
			</termGrp>
		</ntig>
		<descrip type="definition">Academic programs that connect directly to New York State’s workforce demands that are not being met by the current or projected supply of college graduates. Occupations are considered high need if they are projected to have a large number of total openings, a high growth rate, or a combination of a significant number of total openings and positive growth.   </descrip>
</langSet>
</termEntry>
<termEntry>
	<langSet xml:lang="en">
		<ntig>
			<termGrp>
				<term>HIGH SCHOOL STATUS</term>
			</termGrp>
		</ntig>
		<descrip type="definition">The high school status of a student as of the current term.  Required on SIRIS submissions only for FIRST-TIME and TRANSFER students.   </descrip>
		<descrip type="example">[SIRIS STUDENT element SP050] </descrip>
		<descrip type="example">SIRIS reporting codes are as follows: </descrip>
		<descrip type="example">1  High school graduate </descrip>
		<descrip type="example">2  Home school graduate </descrip>
		<descrip type="example">3  GED recipient </descrip>
		<descrip type="example">4  High school on-going </descrip>
		<descrip type="example">5  Non-HS graduate </descrip>
		<descrip type="example">6  Unknown </descrip>
	</langSet>
</termEntry>
<termEntry>
	<langSet xml:lang="en">
		<ntig>
			<termGrp>
				<term>HIGHER EDUCATION FOR THE JUSTICE-INVOLVED (HEJI)</term>
			</termGrp>
		</ntig>
		<descrip type="definition">SUNY's outreach and course delivery to individuals impacted by the legal system.  </descrip>
		<descrip type="example">[SIRIS STUDENT element SE025-code 15] </descrip>
</langSet>
</termEntry>
<termEntry>
	<langSet xml:lang="en">
		<ntig>
			<termGrp>
				<term>HIGHER EDUCATION HISTORY</term>
			</termGrp>
		</ntig>
		<descrip type="definition">The enrollment status of a student at the reporting institution as of the current term.   </descrip>
		<descrip type="example">[SIRIS STUDENT element SE020] </descrip>
		<descrip type="example">SIRIS reporting codes are as follows: </descrip>
		<descrip type="example">  1  UNDERGRADUATE, FIRST-TIME </descrip>
		<descrip type="example">  2  UNDERGRADUATE, TRANSFER </descrip>
		<descrip type="example">  3  UNDERGRADUATE, TRANSITION </descrip>
		<descrip type="example">  4  UNDERGRADUATE, CONTINUING/RETURNING </descrip>
		<descrip type="example">  5  CONCRRENTLY ENROLLED IN HIGH SCHOOL </descrip>
		<descrip type="example">  6  NEW GRADUATE STUDENT </descrip>
		<descrip type="example">  7  GRADUATE STUDENT CONTINUING/RETURNING </descrip>
		<descrip type="example">  8  CROSS-REGISTERED </descrip>
		<descrip type="example">  9  JOINT PROGRAM </descrip>
		<descrip type="example">10  Unknown (seldom to be used) </descrip>
</langSet>
</termEntry>
<termEntry>
	<langSet xml:lang="en">
		<ntig>
			<termGrp>
				<term>HIGHEST EARNED DEGREE AND/OR AWARD</term>
			</termGrp>
		</ntig>
		<descrip type="definition">The highest degree or certificate earned by an individual. </descrip>
		<descrip type="example">[SIRIS STUDENT element SP040] </descrip>
		<descrip type="example">SIRIS reporting codes are as follows: </descrip>
		<descrip type="example">  1  Undergraduate certificate </descrip>
		<descrip type="example">  2  AAS/AOS </descrip>
		<descrip type="example">  3  AA/AS </descrip>
		<descrip type="example">  4  Baccalaureate </descrip>
		<descrip type="example">  5  Master </descrip>
		<descrip type="example">  6  Graduate certificate </descrip>
		<descrip type="example">  7  Doctorate </descrip>
		<descrip type="example">  8  First Professional </descrip>
		<descrip type="example">  9  No degree </descrip>
		<descrip type="example">10  Unknown </descrip>
		<descrip type="example">Required for all UNDERGRADUATE TRANSFER and NEW GRADUATE students.  If reported for UNDERGRADUATE FIRST-TIME STUDENTS, Highest Earned Degree and/or Award must be reported as “no degree”. </descrip>
</langSet>
</termEntry>
<termEntry>
	<langSet xml:lang="en">
		<ntig>
			<termGrp>
				<term>HISPANIC ORIGIN</term>
			</termGrp>
		</ntig>
		<descrip type="definition">A student’s Hispanic, Latino, or Spanish origin, regardless of RACE. </descrip>
		<descrip type="example">[SIRIS STUDENT element SS130, SIRIS DEGREE element DS110] </descrip>
		<descrip type="example">SIRIS reporting codes are as follows: </descrip>
		<descrip type="example"> 1  Non-Hispanic </descrip>
		<descrip type="example"> 2  Dominican </descrip>
		<descrip type="example"> 3  Mexican </descrip>
		<descrip type="example"> 4  Puerto Rican </descrip>
		<descrip type="example"> 5  Central American </descrip>
		<descrip type="example"> 6  South American </descrip>
		<descrip type="example"> 7  Other Hispanic/Latino </descrip>
		<descrip type="example"> 8  Unknown  </descrip>
		<descrip type="example"> 9  Hispanic (no longer used) </descrip>
		<descrip type="example">10 Cuban </descrip>
</langSet>
</termEntry>
<termEntry>
	<langSet xml:lang="en">
		<ntig>
			<termGrp>
				<term>HOME INSTITUTION</term>
			</termGrp>
		</ntig>
		<descrip type="definition">The institution of primary registration for a student attending a SUNY institution.  In most cases, the reporting institution is the home institution.   
			The reporting institution is not the home institution for CROSS-REGISTERED students.  Examples of this include:  1) students from another institution attending the reporting institution under an authorized cross registration program, 2) students from another institution enrolled in an Overseas Academic Program administered by the reporting institution, and 3) students from another institution engaged in accessory instruction at the reporting institution (applicable to ESF, Cornell, and Ceramics only). </descrip>
</langSet>
</termEntry>
<termEntry>
	<langSet xml:lang="en">
		<ntig>
			<termGrp>
				<term>HOME INSTITUTION STUDENT</term>
			</termGrp>
		</ntig>
		<descrip type="definition">A student whose HOME INSTITUTION is the reporting institution.  This is the population typically used for official HEADCOUNT reporting for both internal and external purposes (including NYS Education Department and IPEDS surveys). </descrip>
		<descrip type="example">[See SIRIS STUDENT element SE010 ADMISSION STATUS.  Home institution students are those coded 1-5.] </descrip>
</langSet>
</termEntry>
<termEntry>
	<langSet xml:lang="en">
		<ntig>
			<termGrp>
				<term>HONORS</term>
			</termGrp>
		</ntig>
		<descrip type="definition">Honors courses are offered to students enrolled in Honors programs and colleges. Because Honors courses are often taught in a seminar format, class size is usually small (20 or fewer students).  Honors courses vary widely insofar as they span the academic disciplines; however, they often incorporate learning outcomes that focus on developing effective skills in research, critical thinking, problem-solving, and written and oral communication--skills that are essential for creating sophisticated scholarly works. </descrip>
</langSet>
</termEntry>
<termEntry>
	<langSet xml:lang="en">
		<ntig>
			<termGrp>
				<term>HYBRID</term>
			</termGrp>
		</ntig>
		<descrip type="definition">A SECTION where a portion (0.01% - 99.9%) of the direct instruction of the course section’s curricular content is delivered to the student via an online communication method and the remaining  portion of the direct instruction is delivered face-to-face. </descrip>
		<descrip type="example">[See SIRIS TERM/SECTION element TT080 ONLINE INSTRUCTION TYPE.  Hybrid code is 5.] </descrip>
</langSet>
</termEntry>
<termEntry>
	<langSet xml:lang="en">
		<ntig>
			<termGrp>
				<term>HYFLEX</term>
			</termGrp>
		</ntig>
		<descrip type="definition">A SECTION that combines online and face-to-face instruction simultaneously into one single course section.  Students are able to participate in class in different ways, as they choose to, among the options provided by the instructor:  as a synchronous distance learner (via real-time, video-streaming), as an asynchronous distance learner (accessing materials, recorded lectures, and responding at a later time), or as a face-to-face learner (physically present in the classroom with the instructor).  The key component of a HYFLEX section is flexibility for the student, who can participate by way of their chosen modality from course meeting to course meeting.   </descrip>
		<descrip type="example">[See SIRIS TERM/SECTION element TT080 ONLINE INSTRUCTION TYPE.  Hyflex code is 6.] </descrip>
</langSet>
</termEntry>
<termEntry>
	<langSet xml:lang="en">
		<ntig>
			<termGrp>
				<term>IMPUTED CREDIT HOURS</term>
			</termGrp>
		</ntig>
		<descrip type="definition">See EQUIVALENT CREDIT HOURS </descrip>
	</langSet>
</termEntry>
<termEntry>
	<langSet xml:lang="en">
		<ntig>
			<termGrp>
				<term>IN A PROGRAM, MAJOR NOT CHOSEN (aka UNDECLARED MAJOR)</term>
			</termGrp>
		</ntig>
		<descrip type="definition">A MATRICULATED student enrolled at the reporting institution who has not yet chosen or is not eligible to choose a major field of study.   </descrip>
		<descrip type="example">To report such a student on SIRIS, submit SIRIS STUDENT element SE030 ACADEMIC PROGRAM ID as “null” and supply the code for SIRIS STUDENT element SE035 ACADEMIC AWARD LEVEL – PRIMARY as appropriate to the level of degree the student is pursuing.  </descrip>
</langSet>
</termEntry>
<termEntry>
	<langSet xml:lang="en">
		<ntig>
			<termGrp>
				<term>INCOME FUND REIMBURSABLE (IFR) CREDIT COURSES</term>
			</termGrp>
		</ntig>
		<descrip type="definition">Self-supporting instructional activities, such as contract courses and most summer courses at state-operated institutions.  See also SUTRA. </descrip>
</langSet>
</termEntry>
<termEntry>
	<langSet xml:lang="en">
		<ntig>
			<termGrp>
				<term>INSTRUCTION TYPE</term>
			</termGrp>
		</ntig>
		<descrip type="definition">The primary instructional mode of a SECTION. </descrip>
		<descrip type="example">[SIRIS TERM SECTION element TT090]  </descrip>
		<descrip type="example">SIRIS reporting codes are as follows: </descrip>
		<descrip type="example"> 1  Lecture </descrip>
		<descrip type="example"> 2  Seminar </descrip>
		<descrip type="example"> 3  Recitation/quiz/discussion </descrip>
		<descrip type="example"> 4  Laboratory </descrip>
		<descrip type="example"> 5  Tutorial </descrip>
		<descrip type="example"> 6  Independent study </descrip>
		<descrip type="example"> 7  Programmed instruction </descrip>
		<descrip type="example"> 8  Studio </descrip>
		<descrip type="example"> 9  Practicum </descrip>
		<descrip type="example">10 Internship </descrip>
		<descrip type="example">11 Lecture/lab/recitation (joint) </descrip>
		<descrip type="example">12 Mentored individual learning (for Empire State College use only) </descrip>
		<descrip type="example">13 Advanced graduate research </descrip>
		<descrip type="example">14 Co-operative education </descrip>
</langSet>
</termEntry>
<termEntry>
	<langSet xml:lang="en">
		<ntig>
			<termGrp>
				<term>INTERNSHIP</term>
			</termGrp>
		</ntig>
		<descrip type="definition">Applied learning experiences for which a student may earn academic credit in an agreed-upon, short-term, supervised workplace activity, which may be related to a student’s major field or area of interest. The work can be full or part-time, on or off campus, paid or unpaid. Some institutions offer both credit and non-credit bearing internships. Internships integrate classroom knowledge and theory with practical application and skills developed in professional or community settings. This definition does not include internships that are required components of a registered program leading to NYS licensure or certification (e.g., teacher preparation, social work, dental hygiene). An internship is distinct from community service or service learning.  This is an Applied Learning Activity.  </descrip>
		<descrip type="example">[See SIRIS TERM SECTION element TT090 INSTRUCTION TYPE] </descrip>
</langSet>
</termEntry>
<termEntry>
	<langSet xml:lang="en">
		<ntig>
			<termGrp>
				<term>INTERNSHIP TYPE</term>
			</termGrp>
		</ntig>
		<descrip type="definition">Describes the specific type of internship </descrip>
		<descrip type="example">[SIRIS TERM SECTION element TT095]  </descrip>
		<descrip type="example">SIRIS reporting codes are as follows: </descrip>
		<descrip type="example">1  Formal Internship – paid </descrip>
		<descrip type="example">2  Formal Internship – unpaid </descrip>
		<descrip type="example">3  Independent Internship – paid </descrip>
		<descrip type="example">4  Independent Internship – unpaid </descrip>
		<descrip type="example">Note that as of Fall 2016, this element is no longer required when reporting internship activities or being used by SUNY System Administration. </descrip>
</langSet>
</termEntry>
<termEntry>
	<langSet xml:lang="en">
		<ntig>
			<termGrp>
				<term>IPEDS (INTEGRATED POSTSECONDARY EDUCATION DATA SYSTEM)</term>
			</termGrp>
		</ntig>
		<descrip type="definition">A system of interrelated surveys conducted annually by the U.S. Department’s National Center for Education Statistics (NCES). IPEDS gathers information from every college, university, and technical and vocational institution that participates in the federal student financial aid programs.  The Higher Education Act of 1965, as amended, requires that institutions that participate in federal student aid programs report data on enrollments, program completions, graduation rates, faculty and staff, finances, institutional prices, and student financial aid.  These data are made available to students and parents through the College Navigator college search Website and to researchers and others through the IPEDS Data Center. </descrip>
	</langSet>
</termEntry>
<termEntry>
	<langSet xml:lang="en">
		<ntig>
			<termGrp>
				<term>JOINT DEGREE / PROGRAM</term>
			</termGrp>
		</ntig>
		<descrip type="definition">See COMBINED ACADEMIC PROGRAM 
		If the degrees are to be awarded by different institutions, the program of study is developed and/or provided jointly by those institutions. </descrip>
	</langSet>
</termEntry>
<termEntry>
	<langSet xml:lang="en">
		<ntig>
			<termGrp>
				<term>JUNIOR</term>
			</termGrp>
		</ntig>
		<descrip type="definition">A STUDENT LEVEL derived as follows: 
			A STUDENT IN A BACCALAUREATE DEGREE PROGRAM who has accumulated 60 or more and fewer than 90 CREDIT HOURS.  </descrip>
		<descrip type="example">[See SIRIS STUDENT elements SE030 ACADEMIC PROGRAM ID – PRIMARY and SE110 ACCUMULATED CREDIT HOURS]  </descrip>
</langSet>
</termEntry>
<termEntry>
	<langSet xml:lang="en">
		<ntig>
			<termGrp>
				<term>LEADERSHIP</term>
			</termGrp>
		</ntig>
		<descrip type="definition">An attribute used to describe a course section whose content has been specifically designed to develop or strengthen the student’s capacity to lead effectively. </descrip>
	</langSet>
</termEntry>
<termEntry>
	<langSet xml:lang="en">
		<ntig>
			<termGrp>
				<term>LECTURE</term>
			</termGrp>
		</ntig>
		<descrip type="definition">:  Lecture describes instruction where new material is presented by the instructor(s) with or without some discussion, but discussion is not the primary purpose of the meeting. </descrip>
</langSet>
</termEntry>
<termEntry>
	<langSet xml:lang="en">
		<ntig>
			<termGrp>
				<term>LIMITED ENGLISH PROFICIENCY</term>
			</termGrp>
		</ntig>
		<descrip type="definition">A student who has limited ability in speaking, reading, writing, or understanding the English language, and (1) whose native language is a language other than English; or (2) who lives in a family or community environment in which a language other than English is the dominant language. </descrip>
</langSet>
</termEntry>
<termEntry>
	<langSet xml:lang="en">
		<ntig>
			<termGrp>
				<term>LOCATION TYPE</term>
			</termGrp>
		</ntig>
		<descrip type="definition">Where a course SECTION is taught. </descrip>
		<descrip type="example">[SIRIS TERM SECTION element TT160] </descrip>
		<descrip type="example">SIRIS reporting codes are as follows: </descrip>
		<descrip type="example">1  On-campus </descrip>
		<descrip type="example">2  Another college </descrip>
		<descrip type="example">3  Clinical facility </descrip>
		<descrip type="example">4  Student selected site for distance learning </descrip>
		<descrip type="example">5  High school </descrip>
		<descrip type="example">6  Correctional facility </descrip>
		<descrip type="example">7  Study abroad – your program </descrip>
		<descrip type="example">8  Study abroad – other college </descrip>
		<descrip type="example">9  Community off-campus site </descrip>
		<descrip type="example">10 Multiple Location (On Campus/Abroad) </descrip>
	</langSet>
</termEntry>
<termEntry>
	<langSet xml:lang="en">
		<ntig>
			<termGrp>
				<term>LOWER DIVISION COURSE</term>
			</termGrp>
		</ntig>
		<descrip type="definition">A course directed primarily at LOWER DIVISION STUDENTS. </descrip>
</langSet>
</termEntry>
<termEntry>
	<langSet xml:lang="en">
		<ntig>
			<termGrp>
				<term>LOWER DIVISION STUDENT (IN A PROGRAM)</term>
			</termGrp>
		</ntig>
		<descrip type="definition">In a Bachelor's Program - a STUDENT IN A BACCALAUREATE DEGREE PROGRAM who has accumulated 60 or fewer CREDIT HOURS.   
			In Programs below the Bachelor's Level - an UNDERGRADUATE STUDENT IN A DIPLOMA, CERTIFICATE or ASSOCIATE DEGREE PROGRAM is always considered a lower division student. </descrip>
</langSet>
</termEntry>
<termEntry>
	<langSet xml:lang="en">
		<ntig>
			<termGrp>
				<term>MATRICULATED</term>
			</termGrp>
		</ntig>
		<descrip type="definition">A student who has been accepted into and is enrolled in an ACADEMIC PROGRAM (in the broad sense) at the reporting institution.  Meaning, a student who has been accepted into a specific ACADEMIC PROGRAM (major) or one who has committed to pursuing a degree at a specific AWARD LEVEL (such as bachelors) but not yet chosen a specific field of study. </descrip>
</langSet>
</termEntry>
<termEntry>
	<langSet xml:lang="en">
		<ntig>
			<termGrp>
				<term>MATRICULATION DATE</term>
			</termGrp>
		</ntig>
		<descrip type="definition">The beginning date of the earliest semester in which the student was reported as either enrolled in a specific ACADEMIC PROGRAM of study or was reported as being &quot;IN A PROGRAM, MAJOR NOT CHOSEN&quot;.  For purposes of establishing this date, terms for which the student was reported as &quot;not in a program&quot; are not to be considered.  </descrip>
</langSet>
</termEntry>
<termEntry>
	<langSet xml:lang="en">
		<ntig>
			<termGrp>
				<term>MICROCREDENTIAL</term>
			</termGrp>
		</ntig>
		<descrip type="definition">a focused credential that can be earned in a short timeframe and is designed to provide in-demand skills, know-how and experience.  Stackable microcredentials can also provide a pathway to a certificate or full degree. </descrip>
</langSet>
</termEntry>
<termEntry>
	<langSet xml:lang="en">
		<ntig>
			<termGrp>
				<term>MILITARY SERVICE STATUS</term>
			</termGrp>
		</ntig>
		<descrip type="definition">The status of a student in regards to service in the U.S. Army, Navy, Air Force, Marine Corps, or Coast Guard. </descrip>
		<descrip type="example">[SIRIS STUDENT element SS160] </descrip>
		<descrip type="example">SIRIS reporting codes are as follows: </descrip>
		<descrip type="example">1  Active military duty </descrip>
		<descrip type="example">2  Dependent of active military duty </descrip>
		<descrip type="example">3  Veteran </descrip>
		<descrip type="example">4  National Guard or Active Reserve </descrip>
		<descrip type="example">5  Other (not applicable or unknown) </descrip>
		<descrip type="example">6  Dependent of veteran </descrip>
</langSet>
</termEntry>
<termEntry>
	<langSet xml:lang="en">
		<ntig>
			<termGrp>
				<term>MULTISTATE LONGITUDINAL DATA EXCHANGE (MLDE)</term>
			</termGrp>
		</ntig>
		<descrip type="definition">A system to exchange individual-level education and workforce data between states. </descrip>
</langSet>
</termEntry>
<termEntry>
	<langSet xml:lang="en">
		<ntig>
			<termGrp>
				<term>NATIONAL COMMUNITY COLLEGE BENCHMARKING PROJECT (NCCBP)</term>
			</termGrp>
		</ntig>
		<descrip type="definition">A standardized nation-wide benchmark reporting process established in 2004 by Johnson County Community College (Kansas) in conjunction with other community colleges across the United States.
			The project is designed to help demonstrate institutional effectiveness to federal, state, and accrediting agencies, which require comparisons with others on effectiveness and outcome measures. </descrip>
</langSet>
</termEntry>
<termEntry>
	<langSet xml:lang="en">
		<ntig>
			<termGrp>
				<term>NATIONAL STUDENT CLEARINGHOUSE</term>
			</termGrp>
		</ntig>
		<descrip type="definition">A national database that lenders, loan service providers, guaranty agencies, schools, and students can access to verify student enrollment and degree information.  SUNY System Administration utilizes these data for tracking transfers to non-SUNY institutions and for EDUCATIONAL OUTCOMES (EO) reporting. </descrip>
</langSet>
</termEntry>
<termEntry>
	<langSet xml:lang="en">
		<ntig>
			<termGrp>
				<term>NET PRICE</term>
			</termGrp>
		</ntig>
		<descrip type="definition">The Higher Education Opportunity Act of 2008 defines institutional net price as “the average yearly price actually charged to first-time, full-time undergraduate students receiving student aid at an institution of higher education after deducting such aid.”  In IPEDS, average institutional net price is generated by subtracting the average amount of federal, state/local government, or institutional grant and scholarship aid from the total cost of attendance.  Total cost of attendance is the sum of published tuition and required fees (lower of in-district or in-state for public institutions), books and supplies, and the weighted average for room and board and other expenses.  Cost of attendance data are collected in the Institutional Characteristics (IC) component of IPEDS, and financial aid data are collected in the Student Financial Aid (SFA) component of IPEDS. </descrip>
</langSet>
</termEntry>
<termEntry>
	<langSet xml:lang="en">
		<ntig>
			<termGrp>
				<term>NET PRICE CALCULATOR</term>
			</termGrp>
		</ntig>
		<descrip type="definition">Per the National Center for Education Statistics (NCES), in accordance with the Higher Education Opportunity Act of 2008 (HEOA), by October 29, 2011, each postsecondary institution that participates in Title IV federal student aid programs must post a net price calculator on its website that uses institutional data to provide estimated net price information to current and prospective students and their families based on a student’s individual circumstances.  This calculator should allow students to calculate an estimated net price of attendance at an institution (defined as cost (price) of attendance minus grant and scholarship aid) based on what similar students paid in a previous year.  The net price calculator is required for all Title IV institutions that enroll full-time, first-time degree or certificate-seeking undergraduate students. 
			Institutions may meet this requirement by using the U.S. Department of Education’s Net Price Calculator template or by developing their own customized calculator that includes, at a minimum, the same elements as the Department’s template.  
			Institutions that choose to customize or build their own net price calculator must include, at a minimum, the following input and output elements: 
			Input elements must include: 
				- Data elements to approximate the student’s Expected Family Contribution (EFC), such as income, number in family, and dependency status or factors that estimate dependency status (an institution may use either Federal Methodology or Institutional Methodology to approximate the student’s EFC) 
			Output elements must include:  
				- Estimated total price of attendance; 
				- Estimated tuition and fees; 
				- Estimated room and board; 
				- Estimated books and supplies; 
				- Estimated other expenses (personal expenses, transportation, etc.); 
				- Estimated total grant aid; 
				- Estimated net price; 
				- Percent of the cohort (full-time, first-time students) that received grant aid; and 
				- Caveats and disclaimers, as indicated in the HEOA. </descrip>
	</langSet>
</termEntry>
<termEntry>
	<langSet xml:lang="en">
		<ntig>
			<termGrp>
				<term>NEW GRADUATE STUDENT</term>
			</termGrp>
		</ntig>
		<descrip type="definition">A GRADUATE STUDENT whose first enrollment as a graduate student at the reporting institution occurs during the current term.  </descrip>
	</langSet>
</termEntry>
<termEntry>
	<langSet xml:lang="en">
		<ntig>
			<termGrp>
				<term>NEW YORK RESIDENT</term>
			</termGrp>
		</ntig>
		<descrip type="definition">A student who is a citizen of the United States or holds Legal Permanent Resident status or is an UNDOCUMENTED ALIEN and whose PERMANENT RESIDENCE for purposes of determining tuition charges is New York State.   
			For state-operated campuses, see SUPPORTING DOCUMENT "Revised Policy on Residency for Tuition Purposes at the State-Operated Campus"
			For community colleges, residency can be determined in relation to charge-back status.  See Section 6301 of the Education Law.  </descrip>
	</langSet>
</termEntry>
<termEntry>
	<langSet xml:lang="en">
		<ntig>
			<termGrp>
				<term>NON-CREDIT COURSE</term>
			</termGrp>
		</ntig>
		<descrip type="definition">:  A course offered by an institution which cannot qualify as a CREDIT COURSE; i.e., those for which regular college credit is not awarded and which cannot be used to meet the requirements for a degree, diploma, or certificate awarded by the institution.  </descrip>
	</langSet>
</termEntry>
<termEntry>
	<langSet xml:lang="en">
		<ntig>
			<termGrp>
				<term>NON-CREDIT COURSE STUDENT</term>
			</termGrp>
		</ntig>
		<descrip type="definition">A student enrolled exclusively in one or more NON-CREDIT COURSES which do not generate EQUIVALENT CREDIT HOURS, a student who does not meet the definition of a CREDIT COURSE STUDENT. </descrip>
	</langSet>
</termEntry>
<termEntry>
	<langSet xml:lang="en">
		<ntig>
			<termGrp>
				<term>NON-CREDIT INSTRUCTIONAL ACTIVITIES (NCIA)</term>
			</termGrp>
		</ntig>
		<descrip type="definition">Formally organized and scheduled non-credit activities which are instructional in nature and which require participant registration.  
			Currently, the NCIA Survey conducted by System Administration’s Office of Institutional Research collects only non-state-aided, non-credit instructional activities.  Imputed credit courses or learning center developmental activities are reported elsewhere and are not included in the NCIA.  All other non-credit remedial activities are to be included, such as communications, GED, study skills, math, reading, writing, ESL, entry level computer skills, etc.  This includes both classroom and online non-credit instruction, held both on campus and in off-campus locations.   </descrip>
	</langSet>
</termEntry>
<termEntry>
	<langSet xml:lang="en">
		<ntig>
			<termGrp>
				<term>NON-CREDIT STATE-AIDABLE REMEDIAL COURSE</term>
			</termGrp>
		</ntig>
		<descrip type="definition">The subgroup of NON-CREDIT COURSES which are REMEDIAL or DEVELOPMENTAL and are eligible for state support.  For community colleges, these courses must have received formal approval.   
			See SUPPORTING DOCUMENT &quot;Approval of Non-Credit Courses for State Support&quot; for additional information regarding non-credit courses eligible for state aid.  </descrip>
	</langSet>
</termEntry>
<termEntry>
	<langSet xml:lang="en">
		<ntig>
			<termGrp>
				<term>NOT IN A PROGRAM STUDENT</term>
			</termGrp>
		</ntig>
		<descrip type="definition">A CREDIT COURSE STUDENT enrolled at your institution who has neither formally matriculated nor is considered by the institution to be currently pursuing a specific type of degree or award (such as certificate, associate, bachelors, masters, etc.).  
			To report such a student on SIRIS, submit SIRIS STUDENT element SE030 ACADEMIC PROGRAM ID as “null” and SIRIS STUDENT element SE035 ACADEMIC AWARD LEVEL – PRIMARY as 8.  </descrip>
		<descrip type="example">[See also STUDENT LEVEL and SIRIS STUDENT element SE010 ADMISSION STATUS] </descrip>
	</langSet>
</termEntry>
<termEntry>
	<langSet xml:lang="en">
		<ntig>
			<termGrp>
				<term>ONLINE INSTRUCTION TYPE</term>
			</termGrp>
		</ntig>
		<descrip type="definition">:A SIRIS code used to indicate whether some or all of a course SECTION’S direct instruction (excluding advisement, office hours, homework assignments, and help sessions) occurs online. </descrip>
		<descrip type="example">[SIRIS TERM SECTION element TT080] </descrip>
		<descrip type="example">SIRIS reporting codes are as follows: </descrip>
		<descrip type="example">1  Not online </descrip>
		<descrip type="example">2  Asynchronous online </descrip>
		<descrip type="example">3  Synchronous online </descrip>
		<descrip type="example">4  Combined online </descrip>
		<descrip type="example">5  Hybrid </descrip>
	</langSet>
</termEntry>
<termEntry>
	<langSet xml:lang="en">
		<ntig>
			<termGrp>
				<term>ONLINE STUDENT STATUS</term>
			</termGrp>
		</ntig>
		<descrip type="definition">Indicates the proportion of QUALIFIED ONLINE CREDITS that a student is taking as of the given term’s census date at the reporting campus. 
			[See QUALIFIED ONLINE CREDITS]  </descrip>
		<descrip type="example">[SIRIS STUDENT element SE 190 ONLINE STUDENT STATUS – Added in Fall 2020] </descrip>
		<descrip type="example">SIRIS reporting codes are as follows: </descrip>
		<descrip type="example">1 None </descrip>
		<descrip type="example">2 Some Online </descrip>
		<descrip type="example">3 Exclusively Online </descrip>
		<descrip type="example">4 Not Applicable: All enrolled course sections are Non-Qualified Credits sections. (Qualified Total Online Credits* = 0)   </descrip>
	</langSet>
</termEntry>
<termEntry>
	<langSet xml:lang="en">
		<ntig>
			<termGrp>
				<term>ONLINE PROGRAM</term>
			</termGrp>
		</ntig>
		<descrip type="definition">An academic program that offers 50% or more of the course requirements in an online or distance format.  The 50% standard includes only courses offered in their entirety via distance education, not courses utilizing mixed delivery methods.   </descrip>
	</langSet>
</termEntry>
<termEntry>
	<langSet xml:lang="en">
		<ntig>
			<termGrp>
				<term>OPEN EDUCATIONAL RESOURCES (OER)</term>
			</termGrp>
		</ntig>
		<descrip type="definition">Teaching, learning, and research resources that reside in the public domain or have been released under an intellectual property license that permits repurposing by others. </descrip>
		<descrip type="example">[SIRIS TERM SECTION element SPECIAL SECTION CURRICULAR ATTRIBUTE TT210 – CODE 28] </descrip>
	</langSet>
</termEntry>
<termEntry>
	<langSet xml:lang="en">
		<ntig>
			<termGrp>
				<term>OPEN SUNY</term>
			</termGrp>
		</ntig>
		<descrip type="definition">SUNY-wide collaboration of online-enabled learning opportunities.  Open SUNY is not a degree program or a school; it’s a seamless way for students to access courses, degrees, professors, and rich academics of all 64 SUNY campuses flexibly through online formats.   
			Discontinued and replaced by SUNY ONLINE. </descrip>
	</langSet>
</termEntry>
<termEntry>
	<langSet xml:lang="en">
		<ntig>
			<termGrp>
				<term>OPEN SUNY+</term>
			</termGrp>
		</ntig>
		<descrip type="definition">A subset of programs offered through Open SUNY that bring an additional layer of support for students and faculty.  Students in Open SUNY+ degree programs have access to high-touch support, including a personal concierge, help desk, and online tutoring.  Open SUNY+ programs receive the Open SUNY+ designation after being nominated by their campus and reviewed and approved by Open SUNY.   
		Discontinued.  </descrip>
		<descrip type="example">[SIRIS STUDENT element SPECIAL POPULATION CODE – CODE 12] </descrip>
	</langSet>
</termEntry>
<termEntry>
	<langSet xml:lang="en">
		<ntig>
			<termGrp>
				<term>OVERSEAS ACADEMIC PROGRAM (OAP)</term>
			</termGrp>
		</ntig>
		<descrip type="definition">An instructional program taught in an overseas location either in collaboration with an international institution or by faculty from the SUNY college administering the OAP.  Typically the program is a semester long sequence of courses whose content is enhanced by the location of instruction.   An OAP must be reviewed and approved by SUNY System Administration’s Office of International Programs and upon approval is assigned a unique code to be used for reporting purposes.   
			Enrollment in an OAP is generally open to students cross-registering from colleges other than the administering institution.  If the student is cross-registering from another SUNY institution, both the student’s home institution and the college administering the OAP should report the student’s registration.   
			Some OAPs are established as EXCHANGE PROGRAMS with overseas colleges or universities in which SUNY students go abroad and students from the international college enroll at the SUNY college administering the OAP.      
			For state-operated institutions, a participating student’s HOME INSTITUTION will get the HEADCOUNT for that student, regardless of which campus’s authorized OAP he or she is enrolled in.  A state-op will only get FTE for OAP activity if a member of its teaching staff is accompanying the students abroad and providing credit-bearing academic instruction. 
			For community colleges, a participating student’s HOME INSTITUTION will also get the HEADCOUNT for that student, regardless of which campus’s authorized OAP he or she is enrolled in.  However, a community college will get FTE as well for credit-bearing academic activity occurring through one of its authorized OAPs, regardless of whether or not a member or its teaching staff is accompanying the students abroad or providing the academic instruction. </descrip>
		<descrip type="example">[See SIRIS STUDENT element SE060 Study Abroad Program ID (for EXCHANGE STUDENTS) and SIRIS TERM SECTION element TT180 Location Site-Study Abroad-Your Program]    </descrip>
	</langSet>
</termEntry>
<termEntry>
	<langSet xml:lang="en">
		<ntig>
			<termGrp>
				<term>P-20W (PREKINDERGARTEN - GRADE 20 WORKFORCE)</term>
			</termGrp>
		</ntig>
		<descrip type="definition">Longitudinal data system that matches student data from preschool through college and into the workforce. </descrip>
	</langSet>
</termEntry>
<termEntry>
	<langSet xml:lang="en">
		<ntig>
			<termGrp>
				<term>PART-TIME STUDENT</term>
			</termGrp>
		</ntig>
		<descrip type="definition">For headcount reporting purposes, 
			Part-time undergraduate - an UNDERGRADUATE STUDENT who is enrolled for less than 12 CREDIT HOURS 
			Part-time graduate - a GRADUATE STUDENT who is enrolled for less than 9 CREDIT HOURS 
			For tuition purposes, 
			All students (UNDERGRADUATE or GRADUATE) who are enrolled for less than 12 CREDIT HOURS 
			In determining part-time status, EQUIVALENT CREDIT HOURS imputed to NON-CREDIT COURSES are included in addition to those CREDIT HOURS in standard CREDIT COURSES.  See glossary entries CREDIT COURSE, REQUIRED NON-CREDIT COURSE, NONCREDIT COURSES FOR SPECIAL STUDENTS, CREDIT HOURS, and EQUIVALENT CREDIT HOURS.  
			The identification of students as full- or part-time is derived from SIRIS STUDENT elements SE020 HIGHER EDUCATION HISTORY and SE070 TOTAL CREDIT HOURS.  Official counts come from the Early Student submission. </descrip>
	</langSet>
</termEntry>
<termEntry>
	<langSet xml:lang="en">
		<ntig>
			<termGrp>
				<term>PERFORMANCE IMPROVEMENT FUND (PIF)</term>
			</termGrp>
		</ntig>
		<descrip type="definition">A SUNY System Administration initiative to bring together funds from the enacted budget of the State of New York and other State appropriations under one umbrella to support the strategic priorities of the System and campuses university-wide funding programs. In 2015, as part of SUNY Excels, campuses submitted performance improvement plans to address five key areas: access, completion, success, inquiry, and engagement.  These Performance Improvement Plans include a narrative on campus’ strategic priorities and data commitments through 2020-21 on a standard series of metrics.  The PIF program competition awards support campuses whose Performance Improvement Plan focuses on shaping educational strategy, strengthening student recruitment and success infrastructure, enhancing diversity and inclusion across the System, and promoting knowledge creation, creativity, and translation. </descrip>
	</langSet>
</termEntry>
<termEntry>
	<langSet xml:lang="en">
		<ntig>
			<termGrp>
				<term>PERMANENT RESIDENCE</term>
			</termGrp>
		</ntig>
		<descrip type="definition">Generally the county, state, or country of which the student is a legal resident for purposes of determining tuition charges.  A student's current address would not be his or her permanent residence if residing there mainly for the purpose of attending college.   
			See SUPPORTING DOCUMENT "Revised Policy on Residency for Tuition Purpose at the State-Operated Campus".   </descrip>
		<descrip type="example">[See also SIRIS STUDENT elements SS010 Country of Citizenship, SS060 Permanent County, and SS070 Permanent State/US Territory Code, as well as glossary entries FOREIGN STUDENT AND NEW YORK RESIDENT]  </descrip>
	</langSet>
</termEntry>
<termEntry>
	<langSet xml:lang="en">
		<ntig>
			<termGrp>
				<term>PHYSICAL SPACE INVENTORY (PSI)</term>
			</termGrp>
		</ntig>
		<descrip type="definition">:An inventory of all buildings used – whether they be owned, shared, or leased – by SUNY campuses.  Reported to and maintained by SUNY Construction Fund. 
			Buildings in which campus state-supported activities occur or those for which state funds are used to support programs but owned by private enterprises (foundation, not-for-profit, for profit) are included in this inventory.  Minimally, the rooms used or funded (leased) by campus state operations must be recorded within PSI.   
			The following structures are generally not included:  band shells, fire towers, communications towers, lean-tos, pole barns, transformer pad, picnic pavilion, and water towers. 
			For non-state-supported activities in these non-owned facilities - incubator space, clinical practice, private profit/not-for profit, etc. - the respected spaces can be optionally created in PSI with a chart of account 03 (public service) function.  If necessary, the Construction Fund can establish a special chart of account(s) for these spaces.  This approach enables the campus to record all space without impact on its space analysis results. 
			If the campus has control over the 24-hour assignment of space that is only occasionally scheduled but is used for the duration of the fall semester, then it should be included in the inventory.  For shorter durations or no control of space (e.g. an occasional class in a local high school), the building/space is not to be included.  </descrip>
	</langSet>
</termEntry>
<termEntry>
	<langSet xml:lang="en">
		<ntig>
			<termGrp>
				<term>POSTDOCTORAL STUDENT</term>
			</termGrp>
		</ntig>
		<descrip type="definition">A student who will generally meet these criteria: he or she holds a PhD, EdD, DSci, MD, DVM, DDS, OD, or equivalent earned degree and is at the reporting institution primarily for the development of his or her ability or scholarship.  Excluded are students who are candidates for a degree at the institution registered in CREDIT COURSES or special refresher courses such as &quot;Post Graduate Day in Otorhinolaryngology&quot; or who hold a position with ACADEMIC RANK at the reporting institution.  </descrip>
	</langSet>
</termEntry>
<termEntry>
	<langSet xml:lang="en">
		<ntig>
			<termGrp>
				<term>POST-SECONDARY EMPLOYMENT OUTCOMES (PSEO)</term>
			</termGrp>
		</ntig>
		<descrip type="definition">Experimental tabulations developed by researchers at the U.S. Census Bureau.  PSEO data provide earnings and employment outcomes for college and university graduates by degree level, degree major, and post-secondary institution.  These statistics are generated by matching university transcript data with a national database of jobs, using confidentiality protection mechanisms to protect the underlying data. 
			The PSEO are made possible through data sharing partnerships between universities, university systems, State Departments of Education, State Labor Market Information offices, and the U.S. Census Bureau.  PSEO data are available for post-secondary institutions whose transcript data has been made available to the Census Bureau through a data-sharing agreement. 
			PSEO data can also be accessed via the PSEO Explorer visualization tool. This interactive tool allows for comparisons of employment outcomes through dynamic grouped bar charts and employment flows through Sankey diagrams. 
			See https://lehd.ces.census.gov/data/ for more information. </descrip>
	</langSet>
</termEntry>
<termEntry>
	<langSet xml:lang="en">
		<ntig>
			<termGrp>
				<term>PRIMARY ACADEMIC AWARD LEVEL</term>
			</termGrp>
		</ntig>
		<descrip type="definition">See ACADEMIC AWARD LEVEL – PRIMARY  </descrip>
	</langSet>
</termEntry>
<termEntry>
	<langSet xml:lang="en">
		<ntig>
			<termGrp>
				<term>PROGRAM</term>
			</termGrp>
		</ntig>
		<descrip type="definition">A course of study leading to a formal award given by the reporting institution, such as a degree, diploma, or certificate.  For a listing of programs your institution is authorized to offer, see the Academic Program Campus View area of the DTS portal.  </descrip>
	</langSet>
</termEntry>
<termEntry>
	<langSet xml:lang="en">
		<ntig>
			<termGrp>
				<term>PROGRAM IDENTIFIER</term>
			</termGrp>
		</ntig>
		<descrip type="definition">The unique key consisting of up to 10 numerals associated with each program a SUNY institution is authorized to offer.  These identifiers are kept within the APES system and are listed in the Academic Program Campus View area of the DTS portal. </descrip>
	</langSet>
</termEntry>
<termEntry>
	<langSet xml:lang="en">
		<ntig>
			<termGrp>
				<term>P-TECH</term>
			</termGrp>
		</ntig>
		<descrip type="definition">A student who is participating in the Pathways in Technology Early College High School (P-TECH), one of the New York SED sponsored Early College High School programs.   PTECH programs focus on preparing students for careers in technical, manufacturing and health care fields.   Students are mentored by employees of businesses who partner with the program.   Those completing the full program earn a high school diploma and an associate’s degree.     </descrip>
	</langSet>
</termEntry>
<termEntry>
	<langSet xml:lang="en">
		<ntig>
			<termGrp>
				<term>QUALIFYING CREDIT HOURS (FOR REPORTING/COMPUTING ONLINE RATE/STATUS</term>
			</termGrp>
		</ntig>
		<descrip type="definition">Credit hours which are included in the denominator when computing the percentage of online credits taken by a student in a term or the percentage of online credits taught by faculty in a term.  Qualified credits include all attempted credit hours from reporting campus course sections [Special Course Indicator (CC 025) =1], except credits from sections with: Credit Contact Hour Relationship (TT 100) as Non Instructional Setting (7) AND Instruction Type (TT 090) as Independent Study (6), Practicum(9) or Internship (10). </descrip>
	</langSet>
</termEntry>
<termEntry>
	<langSet xml:lang="en">
		<ntig>
			<termGrp>
				<term>QUALIFYING ONLINE CREDIT HOURS</term>
			</termGrp>
		</ntig>
		<descrip type="definition">Credit hours which are included in the numerator when computing the percentage of online credits taken by a student in a term or the percentage of online credits taught by faculty in a term.  Attempted credits which are counted as online include QUALIFIED CREDITS with Online Instruction Type (TT 080) as Asynchronous Online (2), Synchronous Online (3), or Combined Online (4).  </descrip>
	</langSet>
</termEntry>
<termEntry>
	<langSet xml:lang="en">
		<ntig>
			<termGrp>
				<term>QUANTWAY</term>
			</termGrp>
		</ntig>
		<descrip type="definition">Quantway is an accelerated remedial or developmental quantitative reasoning pathway developed by The Carnegie Foundation. Indicates that this section is a first semester Quantway course section.  Quantway may be one or two course sequence.  The first course usually grants no credit.  While the second course may grant some credit.   </descrip>
		<descrip type="example">[SIRIS TERM SECTION element SPECIAL SECTION CURRICULAR ATTRIBUTE TT210 – Code 21—Quantway I and Code 22—Quantway II] </descrip>
	</langSet>
</termEntry>
<termEntry>
	<langSet xml:lang="en">
		<ntig>
			<termGrp>
				<term>RACE</term>
			</termGrp>
		</ntig>
		<descrip type="definition">The race(s) an individual identifies with. </descrip>
		<descrip type="example">[SIRIS STUDENT element SS150, SIRIS DEGREE element DS120] </descrip>
		<descrip type="example">SIRIS reporting codes are as follows: </descrip>
		<descrip type="example">1  White </descrip>
		<descrip type="example">2  Black or African American </descrip>
		<descrip type="example">3  Asian </descrip>
		<descrip type="example">4  Native Hawaiian or Other Pacific Islander </descrip>
		<descrip type="example">5  American Indian or Alaska Native </descrip>
		<descrip type="example">6  Unknown </descrip>
		<descrip type="example">7  Asian or Pacific Islander (no longer used) </descrip>
		<descrip type="example">For reporting out purposes, the derived IPEDS Race or SUNY Race elements are typically used and are described below.  Both of these derived elements are available in the SUNY Data Warehouse. </descrip>
		<descrip type="example">IPEDS Race Ethnicity includes the following nine categories: </descrip>
		<descrip type="example">Hispanic  </descrip>
		<descrip type="example">American Indian or Alaska Native </descrip>
		<descrip type="example">Asian </descrip>
		<descrip type="example">Black or African American </descrip>
		<descrip type="example">Native Hawaiian or Other Pacific Islander </descrip>
		<descrip type="example">White </descrip>
		<descrip type="example">Two or more races </descrip>
		<descrip type="example">Nonresident alien </descrip>
		<descrip type="example">Unknown </descrip>
		<descrip type="example">The IPEDS Race categories are derived from the information reported in SIRIS elements HISPANIC ORIGIN and RACE and are mapped per IPEDS guidance.  First, if an individual is a nonresident alien according to the visa and citizenship information reported by the institution, then the individual’s IPEDS Race is Nonresident Alien.  Second, if the individual is reported as having Hispanic ethnicity, then the IPEDS Race is Hispanic.  Third, for non-Hispanic United States citizens and permanent residents, the mapping is as follows: </descrip>
		<descrip type="example">If the individual is reported as:                  the IPEDS Race is: </descrip>
		<descrip type="example">American Indian or Alaska Native only   American Indian or Alaska Native  </descrip>
		<descrip type="example">Asian only       Asian  </descrip>
		<descrip type="example">Black or African American only    Black or African American  </descrip>
		<descrip type="example">     Native Hawaiian or Other Pacific Islander only        Native Hawaiian or Other Pacific Islander  </descrip>
		<descrip type="example">White only       White  </descrip>
		<descrip type="example">more than one race category    Two or more races  </descrip>
		<descrip type="example">Otherwise, IPEDS race is Unknown. </descrip>
		<descrip type="example">SUNY Race Ethnicity includes the following ten categories: </descrip>
		<descrip type="example">Hispanic  </descrip>
		<descrip type="example">American Indian or Alaska Native </descrip>
		<descrip type="example">Asian </descrip>
		<descrip type="example">Black or African American </descrip>
		<descrip type="example">Native Hawaiian or Other Pacific Islander  </descrip>
		<descrip type="example">White </descrip>
		<descrip type="example">Two or more races – URM  </descrip>
		<descrip type="example">Two or more races – Non-URM </descrip>
		<descrip type="example">Nonresident alien </descrip>
		<descrip type="example">Unknown </descrip>
		<descrip type="example">SUNY Race is the same as IPEDS Race except SUNY Race separates the IPEDS Two or More Races category into two groups: Two or more races – URM and Two or more races – Non-URM, where URM stands for underrepresented minority.  </descrip>
		<descrip type="example">If an individual is reported as being in more than one race category and one of the races is American Indian or Alaska Native, Black or African American, or Native Hawaiian or Other Pacific Islander, then the individual’s SUNY Race is Two or more races – URM. </descrip>
		<descrip type="example">If an individual is reported as being both White and Asian, then the individual’s SUNY Race is Two or more races – Non URM.   </descrip>
	</langSet>
</termEntry>
<termEntry>
	<langSet xml:lang="en">
		<ntig>
			<termGrp>
				<term>RECRUITMENT</term>
			</termGrp>
		</ntig>
		<descrip type="definition">The actions leading to the enrollment of students. The recruitment process may not be completed until an application and applications fee(s) are received. </descrip>
	</langSet>
</termEntry>
<termEntry>
	<langSet xml:lang="en">
		<ntig>
			<termGrp>
				<term>REMEDIAL COURSE – CONTINUING EDUCATION</term>
			</termGrp>
		</ntig>
		<descrip type="definition">This type of course contains material exclusively at the pre-college level that is not creditable toward a degree and is intended to help prepare a student to be successful with college-level material.  It is designed for students deficient in the general competencies necessary for a regular postsecondary curriculum and whose instruction is concerned with diagnosing, correcting, or improving such basic skills as oral and written communications, reading, analytical concepts, and general study habits and patterns to overcome in part or in whole any particular marked deficiency which interferes with a student's ability to pursue an education objective effectively.  This course is offered through the Community College’s Office of Continuing Education and must have received formal approval from System Administration.  The course contributes toward (AA)FTE in the form of equivalent credit hours and is hence state-aidable for Community Colleges.  
		See SUPPORTING DOCUMENT “Non-Credit Remedial Course Aid” for additional information on aid- eligible remedial courses.   </descrip>
	</langSet>
</termEntry>
<termEntry>
	<langSet xml:lang="en">
		<ntig>
			<termGrp>
				<term>REMEDIAL COURSE – NON-CONTINUING EDUCATION</term>
			</termGrp>
		</ntig>
		<descrip type="definition">This type of course contains material exclusively at the pre-college level that is not creditable toward a degree and is intended to help prepare a student to be successful with college-level material.  It is designed for students deficient in the general competencies necessary for a regular postsecondary curriculum and whose instruction is concerned with diagnosing, correcting, or improving such basic skills as oral and written communications, reading, analytical concepts, and general study habits and patterns to overcome in part or in whole any particular marked deficiency which interferes with a student's ability to pursue an education objective effectively.  This course is not offered through the college’s Office of Continuing Education, does not require approval from System Administration, and is approved through the college’s standard academic course approval process.   The course contributes toward (AA)FTE in the form of equivalent credit hours and is hence state-aidable. </descrip>
	</langSet>
</termEntry>
<termEntry>
	<langSet xml:lang="en">
		<ntig>
			<termGrp>
				<term>REQUIRED NON-CREDIT COURSE</term>
			</termGrp>
		</ntig>
		<descrip type="definition">Primarily found at state-operated campuses, a course which does not carry CREDIT HOURS but is needed to satisfy the requirements of the student’s degree PROGRAM.  For example, this is commonplace in the visual and performing arts.  It can also include required service learning activities. 
		[See also CREDIT COURSE STUDENT, EQUIVALENT CREDIT HOURS and CREDIT HOURS]  </descrip>
	</langSet>
</termEntry>
<termEntry>
	<langSet xml:lang="en">
		<ntig>
			<termGrp>
				<term>RESEARCH</term>
			</termGrp>
		</ntig>
		<descrip type="definition">Mentored, self-directed work that enables students to make an original, intellectual, or creative contribution to the discipline by exploring an issue of interest to them and communicating the results to others.  The projects involve inquiry, design, investigation, discovery, and application.  This is an Applied Learning Activity. </descrip>
	</langSet>
</termEntry>
<termEntry>
	<langSet xml:lang="en">
		<ntig>
			<termGrp>
				<term>RESIDENCY (STUDENT)</term>
			</termGrp>
		</ntig>
		<descrip type="definition">For reporting purposes, a student’s PERMANENT RESIDENCE is categorized into one of the following groups: 
			- New York Resident 
			- Other US (including territories) 
			- International 
			- Unknown</descrip>
	</langSet>
</termEntry>
<termEntry>
	<langSet xml:lang="en">
		<ntig>
			<termGrp>
				<term>RETENTION /PERSISTENCE RATE</term>
			</termGrp>
		</ntig>
		<descrip type="definition">The percentage of students from an entering COHORT who continue to be enrolled at a specific point in time at the reporting institution.  For example, a first-time, full-time COHORT of students in a bachelor’s degree program would typically be assessed at 1, 2, and 3 years out.  Similarly, those in an associate’s degree program would typically be assessed at 1 year out.   </descrip>
	</langSet>
</termEntry>
<termEntry>
	<langSet xml:lang="en">
		<ntig>
			<termGrp>
				<term>RETURNING STUDENT</term>
			</termGrp>
		</ntig>
		<descrip type="definition">See CONTINUING/RETURNING STUDENT </descrip>
	</langSet>
</termEntry>
<termEntry>
	<langSet xml:lang="en">
		<ntig>
			<termGrp>
				<term>REVERSE TRANSFER</term>
			</termGrp>
		</ntig>
		<descrip type="definition">This term is used to describe the process by which a student earns at least the minimum number of credits required to earn a credential at a sending campus (typically a community college) before transferring.  After earning additional credits at the receiving institution (typically a state-operated campus), the student transfers these credits back to the sending campus and earns a credential.  For example, if a student earns at least 30 credits at a community college, then transfers to a state operated campus and earns an additional 30 or more credits, it may be possible to transfer the credits earned at the state-operated campus back to the community college such that the student could earn a 60 credit associate degree.  This process is determined by a number of factors, including the student meeting residency requirements, taking the correct courses to meet degree requirements at the degree awarding campus, and completing the required application and consent forms. </descrip>
	</langSet>
</termEntry>
<termEntry>
	<langSet xml:lang="en">
		<ntig>
			<termGrp>
				<term>RISK ADMISSIONS</term>
			</termGrp>
		</ntig>
		<descrip type="definition">A term used to describe the group of students who fail to meet the normal admission standards of the college or students admitted in recognition of a special talent that merits admission into an ACADEMIC PROGRAM related to this talent which is offered by the institution. </descrip>
	</langSet>
</termEntry>
<termEntry>
	<langSet xml:lang="en">
		<ntig>
			<termGrp>
				<term>SAT/ACT CONVERSION</term>
			</termGrp>
		</ntig>
		<descrip type="defininitio">For many reporting purposes, SUNY System Administration converts a submitted ACT score into an SAT combined Math and Verbal score per the conversion table provided by College Board.  For SELECTIVITY purposes, when more than one score is available, the highest score is used.   </descrip>
		<descrip type="example">[See SIRIS STUDENT elements SP010 and SP020] </descrip>
	</langSet>
</termEntry>
<termEntry>
	<langSet xml:lang="en">
		<ntig>
			<termGrp>
				<term>SEAMLESS TRANSFER</term>
			</termGrp>
		</ntig>
		<descrip type="definition">On December 17, 2012, the SUNY Board of Trustees passed resolution 2012-089 that established the current policy framework governing transfer across the SUNY system (Seamless Transfer).  The policy established guidelines for lower division undergraduate curricula and the transfer of coursework as it related to general education, courses in the major (‘Transfer Path courses’) and credit requirements for associate and baccalaureate degree programs.   </descrip>
	<descrip type="example">[SIRIS COURSE element CC095 Transfer Path Course Indicator; added Spring 2021.] </descrip>
	</langSet>
</termEntry>
<termEntry>
	<langSet xml:lang="en">
		<ntig>
			<termGrp>
				<term>SECTION</term>
			</termGrp>
		</ntig>
		<descrip type="definition">A specific instantiation of student learning activity within a course.  Different sections of a course will vary on any combination of the following:  enrolled student(s), faculty member(s), INSTRUCTION TYPE, time, and location.   
		For example, a single group of students meeting on Monday and Wednesday for lecture and on Friday for a laboratory constitute two sections.  As another example, if the INSTRUCTION TYPE is independent study, each student’s activity is regarded as a separate section because the instructor is meeting with each student individually.  </descrip>
</langSet>
</termEntry>
<termEntry>
	<langSet xml:lang="en">
		<ntig>
			<termGrp>
				<term>SELECTIVITY</term>
			</termGrp>
		</ntig>
		<descrip type="definition">An indicator based on overall academic measures of FIRST-TIME FULL-TIME students.  SUNY utilizes the SAT combined Math and Verbal scores as well as High School Averages for those students who are regular admits (see ADMISSION STATUS) and enrolled in a bachelor's degree program.    
		For SUNY’s purposes, each student's coordinates are plotted based on the highest reported SAT Math and Verbal scores and the reported High School Average.  A campus is assigned to a particular selectivity group if 60% or more of its first-time full-time baccalaureate enrollment lies in that group or a more selective one.   </descrip>
</langSet>
</termEntry>
<termEntry>
	<langSet xml:lang="en">
		<ntig>
			<termGrp>
				<term>SENIOR</term>
			</termGrp>
		</ntig>
		<descrip type="definition">A STUDENT LEVEL derived as follows: A STUDENT IN A BACCALAUREATE DEGREE PROGRAM who has accumulated 90 or more CREDIT HOURS.</descrip>
		<descrip type="example">[See SIRIS STUDENT elements SE030 ACADEMIC PROGRAM – PRIMARY and SE110 ACCUMULATED CREDIT HOURS]  </descrip>
	</langSet>
</termEntry>
<termEntry>
	<langSet xml:lang="en">
		<ntig>
			<termGrp>
				<term>SERVICE LEARNING</term>
			</termGrp>
		</ntig>
		<descrip type="definition">A teaching and learning strategy that integrates meaningful community service with instruction and reflection to enrich the learning experience, teach civic responsibility, and strengthen communities.  Students are not paid for service learning.  This is an Applied Learning Activity. </descrip>
	</langSet>
</termEntry>
<termEntry>
	<langSet xml:lang="en">
		<ntig>
			<termGrp>
				<term>SEX (formerly called GENDER)</term>
			</termGrp>
		</ntig>
		<descrip type="definition">Student’s sex.  This is a required element for all HOME INSTITUTION students and is used to assign a SUNY ID as well as for database matching purposes.  There is no unknown value for this element.  Must be reported as either Male or Female in order to comply with federal and state reporting.  For those with Social Security Identification, this should be the sex designation recorded with the Social Security office.  For international students, this should match the sex designation on the passport. </descrip>
		<descrip type="example">[SIRIS STUDENT element SD070, SIRIS DEGREE element DS060]  </descrip>
		<descrip type="example">SIRIS reporting codes are as follows: </descrip>
		<descrip type="example"> M Male </descrip>
		<descrip type="example"> F   Female  </descrip>
	</langSet>
</termEntry>
<termEntry>
	<langSet xml:lang="en">
		<ntig>
			<termGrp>
				<term>SEXUAL VIOLENCE PREVENTION (SVP) CAMPUS CLIMATE SURVEY</term>
			</termGrp>
		</ntig>
		<descrip type="definition">First administered in academic year 2016-17, this is a campus climate assessment mandated by SUNY Board of Trustees resolution (October 2, 2014) and by NYS Education Law Article 129-B (applicable section effective July 2016).  The survey is administered by all SUNY campuses every other year to both students and employees. Per Section 6445 of the NYS Education Law Article, the student survey/assessment must include questions covering: 
			a. the Title IX Coordinator's role; 
			b. campus policies and procedures addressing sexual assault; 
			c. how and where to report domestic violence, dating violence, stalking or sexual assault as a victim, survivor or witness; 
			d. the availability of resources on and off campus, such as counseling, health and academic assistance; 
			e. the prevalence of victimization and perpetration of domestic violence, dating violence, stalking, or sexual assault on and off campus during a set time period; 
			f. bystander attitudes and behavior; 
			g. whether reporting individuals disclosed to the institution and/or law enforcement, experiences with reporting and institution processes, and reasons why they did or did not report; 
			h. the general awareness of the difference, if any, between the institution's policies and the penal law; and 
			i. general awareness of the definition of affirmative consent. </descrip>
	</langSet>
</termEntry>
<termEntry>
	<langSet xml:lang="en">
		<ntig>
			<termGrp>
				<term>SIMULTANEOUS USAGE</term>
			</termGrp>
		</ntig>
		<descrip type="definition">Simultaneous Usage indicates the use of the same physical space at the same time by two or more sections, and whether student rosters should be merged for instructional workload purposes.</descrip>
		<descrip type="example">[SIRIS TERM SECTION element TT200]  </descrip>
		<descrip type="example">Default is No (0).  (Revised for Spring 2023 Implementation)  </descrip>
		<descrip type="example">No (0): No indicates the section is not cross-listed and does not share the same space with other sections (default). </descrip>
		<descrip type="example">Yes – Unrelated (1):  The section uses the same physical space (building and room) at the same time as another one or more sections. For workload, though, should not be combined with simultaneous section. </descrip>
		<descrip type="example">Yes Cross-listed (2):  The section uses the same physical space (building and room), or online at the same time as another one or more cross-listed sections. For instructional workload, this section and cross-listed simultaneous sections should be treated as one section. </descrip>
	</langSet>
</termEntry>
<termEntry>
	<langSet xml:lang="en">
		<ntig>
			<termGrp>
				<term>SINGLE PARENT</term>
			</termGrp>
		</ntig>
		<descrip type="definition">A student who is not married or who is legally separated from a spouse and (1) has a minor child or children for whom the parent has either custody or joint custody or (2) is pregnant. </descrip>
	</langSet>
</termEntry>
<termEntry>
	<langSet xml:lang="en">
		<ntig>
			<termGrp>
				<term>SIRIS</term>
			</termGrp>
		</ntig>
		<descrip type="definition">SUNY Institutional Research Information System </descrip>
	</langSet>
</termEntry>
<termEntry>
	<langSet xml:lang="en">
		<ntig>
			<termGrp>
				<term>SIRIS COURSE</term>
			</termGrp>
		</ntig>
		<descrip type="definition">A data submission made by each SUNY institution representing the details of the institution’s course catalog.  These courses are linked to the SECTIONS reported on SIRIS TERM SECTION.  See the CS-DTS section of the CONFLUENCE website for the latest data dictionary. </descrip>
	</langSet>
</termEntry>
<termEntry>
	<langSet xml:lang="en">
		<ntig>
			<termGrp>
				<term>SIRIS DEGREE</term>
			</termGrp>
		</ntig>
		<descrip type="definition">A data submission made by each SUNY institution representing the details of the institution’s degrees and other formal awards granted in the specified time period.  See the CS-DTS section of the CONFLUENCE website for the latest data dictionary. </descrip>
</langSet>
</termEntry>
<termEntry>
	<langSet xml:lang="en">
		<ntig>
			<termGrp>
				<term>SIRIS FINANCIAL AID</term>
			</termGrp>
		</ntig>
		<descrip type="definition">A data submission made by each SUNY institution representing the details of financial aid for all students offered, accepted, or disbursed amount(s) for a specific academic year.  See the CS-DTS section of the CONFLUENCE website for the latest data dictionary. </descrip>
	</langSet>
</termEntry>
<termEntry>
	<langSet xml:lang="en">
		<ntig>
			<termGrp>
				<term>SIRIS STUDENT</term>
			</termGrp>
		</ntig>
		<descrip type="example">Early Student (ESS):  For fall and spring semesters only.  A data submission made by each SUNY institution representing academic and demographic attributes of students enrolled in a specific term. Official student HEADCOUNT is based on enrollment reported in this submission.  Required inclusion are all CREDIT COURSE STUDENTS enrolled in at least one SECTION whose CENSUS DATE falls on or prior to the semester’s Early Student cut-off date, as listed below. </descrip>
		<descrip type="example">Fall:  October 15 </descrip>
		<descrip type="example">Spring:  March 15 </descrip>
		<descrip type="example">Optional inclusion are NON-CREDIT COURSE STUDENTS. </descrip>
		<descrip type="example">EOT (End of Term) Student:  For fall, winter (if applicable), spring, and summer semesters.  A data submission made by each SUNY institution representing academic and demographic attributes of students enrolled in a specific term.  Required inclusion are all CREDIT COURSE STUDENTS enrolled in at least one SECTION whose CENSUS DATE falls on or prior to the semester’s EOT Student cut-off date, as listed below. </descrip>
		<descrip type="example">Summer: September 15 </descrip>
		<descrip type="example">Fall:  January 15 </descrip>
		<descrip type="example">Winter:  February 15 </descrip>
		<descrip type="example">Spring:  June 1 </descrip>
		<descrip type="example">Optional inclusion are NON-CREDIT COURSE STUDENTS. </descrip>
		<descrip type="example">EOT Student must be submitted in conjunction with and be consistent with the corresponding SIRIS TERM SECTION submission. </descrip>
		<descrip type="example">See the CS-DTS section of the CONFLUENCE website for the latest data dictionary (which is the same for both Early and EOT).  See SIRIS Appendix O for more detailed reporting information for both Early and EOT Student. </descrip>
	</langSet>
</termEntry>
<termEntry>
	<langSet xml:lang="en">
		<ntig>
			<termGrp>
				<term>SIRIS STUDENT INFORMATION SURVEY</term>
			</termGrp>
		</ntig>
		<descrip type="definition">For fall and spring semesters.  A campus data submission that reports the results of the Student Information Survey taken by students during the registration process for the next major term.   </descrip>
	</langSet>
</termEntry>
<termEntry>
	<langSet xml:lang="en">
		<ntig>
			<termGrp>
				<term>SIRIS STUDENT REVENUE</term>
			</termGrp>
		</ntig>
		<descrip type="definition">(Not required as of 2020-21.)  For the time period July 1 - June 30, submitted on an annual basis. A data submission that collects billings/charges for students who had at least one revenue charge with a transaction date in the time period July 1 – June 30 for various revenue categories (e.g. tuition, room, board, and fee charges).  The revenue charges are reported by URAS accounting codes for state-operated campuses and also by revenue charge categories for all campuses. This file does not collect or report student payment information. The information is a unit record account of summarized information received by the SUNY System Controller’s Office for state-operated campuses and allows similar information to be also collected for community colleges.   </descrip>
	</langSet>
</termEntry>
<termEntry>
	<langSet xml:lang="en">
		<ntig>
			<termGrp>
				<term>SIRIS TERM SECTION</term>
			</termGrp>
		</ntig>
		<descrip type="definition">For fall, winter (if applicable), spring, and summer semesters.  A data submission made by each SUNY institution representing the details of the institution’s course SECTIONS offered during a specific term.  Must be submitted in conjunction with and be consistent with the corresponding SIRIS EOT Student.  See the CS-DTS section of the CONFLUENCE website for the latest data dictionary. </descrip>
	</langSet>
</termEntry>
<termEntry>
	<langSet xml:lang="en">
		<ntig>
			<termGrp>
				<term>SMART SCHOLARS (EARLY COLLEGE HIGH SCHOOL)</term>
			</termGrp>
		</ntig>
		<descrip type="definition">SUNY institutions partner with public school districts to create early college high schools that provide students with the opportunity and preparation to accelerate the completion of their high school studies while earning a minimum of twenty-four and up to sixty transferable college credits at the same time.  Smart Scholars partnerships are designated as such by the State Education Department.  Smart Scholars is targeted to students who are traditionally underrepresented in postsecondary education and serves to increase high school graduation and college completion rates, while reducing student tuition costs as a result of the compressed time needed to complete a college degree.  </descrip>
	</langSet>
</termEntry>
<termEntry>
	<langSet xml:lang="en">
		<ntig>
			<termGrp>
				<term>SOPHOMORE</term>
			</termGrp>
		</ntig>
		<descrip type="definition">A STUDENT LEVEL derived as follows: 
			Bachelor's level programs - A STUDENT IN A BACCALAUREATE DEGREE PROGRAM who has accumulated 30 or more and fewer than 60 CREDIT HOURS.  
			Non-bachelor's level programs - a STUDENT IN A DIPLOMA, CERTIFICATE or ASSOCIATE DEGREE PROGRAM who has accumulated 30 or more CREDIT HOURS.</descrip>
		<descrip type="example">[See SIRIS STUDENT element SE030 ACADEMIC PROGRAM ID – PRIMARY and SIRIS STUDENT element SE110 ACCUMULATED CREDIT HOURS]  </descrip>
	</langSet>
</termEntry>
<termEntry>
	<langSet xml:lang="en">
		<ntig>
			<termGrp>
				<term>SPECIAL AUDITORS</term>
			</termGrp>
		</ntig>
		<descrip type="definition">A New York State resident aged 60+ who takes a course at no charge on a space-available basis. 
			See Memorandum to Presidents Vol. 74 No. 42, “Guidelines for Course Audit by Older Adults”, found in the SUPPORTING DOCUMENTS.  </descrip>
	</langSet>
</termEntry>
<termEntry>
	<langSet xml:lang="en">
		<ntig>
			<termGrp>
				<term>SPECIAL POPULATION CODE</term>
			</termGrp>
		</ntig>
		<descrip type="definition">A code used to identify students with special characteristics on the SIRIS STUDENT submission. </descrip>
		<descrip type="example">[See SIRIS STUDENT element SE025 SPECIAL POPULAITON CODE] </descrip>
	</langSet>
</termEntry>
<termEntry>
	<langSet xml:lang="en">
		<ntig>
			<termGrp>
				<term>SSN</term>
			</termGrp>
		</ntig>
		<descrip type="definition">The nine-digit social security number administered by the Social Security Administration.  Used for matching purposes.  No other number is to be used as a proxy.   </descrip>
	</langSet>
</termEntry>
<termEntry>
	<langSet xml:lang="en">
		<ntig>
			<termGrp>
				<term>STATE SUPPORTED GRADUATE DIVISION CREDIT HOURS</term>
			</termGrp>
		</ntig>
		<descrip type="definition">In the context of SIRIS STUDENT reporting, the number of graduate CREDIT HOURS in GRADUATE (including FIRST PROFESSIONAL) COURSES eligible for state aid.  Used for estimating the graduate FTE for the current term. </descrip>
		<descrip type="example">[SIRIS STUDENT element SE100] </descrip>
	</langSet>
</termEntry>
<termEntry>
	<langSet xml:lang="en">
		<ntig>
			<termGrp>
				<term>STATE SUPPORTED LOWER DIVISION CREDIT HOURS</term>
			</termGrp>
		</ntig>
		<descrip type="definition">In the context of SIRIS STUDENT reporting, the number of undergraduate CREDIT HOURS in LOWER DIVISION COURSES eligible for state aid.  Includes state-aidable remedial/developmental credit hours.  Used for estimating the lower division FTE for the current term. </descrip>
		<descrip type="example">[SIRIS STUDENT element SE080] </descrip>
	</langSet>
</termEntry>
<termEntry>
	<langSet xml:lang="en">
		<ntig>
			<termGrp>
				<term>STATE SUPPORTED UPPER DIVISION CREDIT HOURS</term>
			</termGrp>
		</ntig>
		<descrip type="definition">In the context of SIRIS STUDENT reporting, the number of undergraduate CREDIT HOURS in UPPER DIVISION COURSES eligible for state aid.  Used for estimating the upper division FTE for the current term. </descrip>
		<descrip type="example">[SIRIS STUDENT element SE090] </descrip>
	</langSet>
</termEntry>
<termEntry>
	<langSet xml:lang="en">
		<ntig>
			<termGrp>
				<term>STATE-AIDABLE AUDITOR</term>
			</termGrp>
		</ntig>
		<descrip type="definition">A student who is officially registered in a credit course, has paid the standard tuition for the course, and whose transcript will acknowledge the course was audited. </descrip>
	</langSet>
</termEntry>
<termEntry>
	<langSet xml:lang="en">
		<ntig>
			<termGrp>
				<term>STATEWIDE LONGITUDINAL DATA SYSTEM (SLDS)</term>
			</termGrp>
		</ntig>
		<descrip type="definition">A data repository or data management coordination at the state level resulting in a single data system that contains secure access to student data from all participating agencies. </descrip>
	</langSet>
</termEntry>
<termEntry>
	<langSet xml:lang="en">
		<ntig>
			<termGrp>
				<term>STATWAY</term>
			</termGrp>
		</ntig>
		<descrip type="definition">Statway integrates developmental mathematics skills and college-level statistics into a collaborative, problem-focused class.  Statway was developed by The Carnegie Foundation as a year-long course.  Course grants some credit.  </descrip>
		<descrip type="example">[SIRIS TERM SECTION element SPECIAL SECTION CURRICULAR ATTRIBUTE TT210 – Code 23—Statway] </descrip>
	</langSet>
</termEntry>
<termEntry>
	<langSet xml:lang="en">
		<ntig>
			<termGrp>
				<term>STEM DISCIPLINES</term>
			</termGrp>
		</ntig>
		<descrip type="definition">Acronym for the fields of study in the categories of science, technology, engineering, and mathematics. Currently, SUNY is using the disciplines identified by the Department of Homeland Security, which can be found at https://www.ice.gov/sevis/stemlist.htm. </descrip>
	</langSet>
</termEntry>
<termEntry>
	<langSet xml:lang="en">
		<ntig>
			<termGrp>
				<term>STUDENT ACHIEVEMENT MEASURE (SAM)</term>
			</termGrp>
		</ntig>
		<descrip type="definition">A national project established to allow post-secondary institutions to more fully account for the outcomes achieved by all incoming students.  SAM tracks cohorts defined by both full and part-time status, and for incoming transfers as well as first-time students.  SAM also accounts for degree completion at both the initial institution as well as subsequent institutions attended.  See https://studentachievementmeasure.org for more information.  SUNY campuses participate on their own as they desire. </descrip>
	</langSet>
</termEntry>
<termEntry>
	<langSet xml:lang="en">
		<ntig>
			<termGrp>
				<term>STUDENT CONTACT HOURS</term>
			</termGrp>
		</ntig>
		<descrip type="definition">The total hours spent by an individual student in scheduled instruction in a particular course SECTION.  Total student contact hours are usually the same as total FACULTY CONTACT HOURS but may differ in those instances when the faculty is not in full/direct supervision of the student. For example, a typical 3-credit Lecture taken in a standard 15-week semester will yield the same 45 contact hours for both student and faculty, while a typical 3-credit Independent Study will yield 45 student contact hours and 0 faculty contact hours.  
			See SUPPORTING DOCUMENT Memorandum to Presidents, Vol. 76, No. 8, “Credit/Contact Hour Relationship”, for more detailed information. </descrip>
		<descrip type="example">[See also SIRIS TERM SECTION element TT120] </descrip>
	</langSet>
</termEntry>
<termEntry>
	<langSet xml:lang="en">
		<ntig>
			<termGrp>
				<term>STUDENT GOAL</term>
			</termGrp>
		</ntig>
		<descrip type="definition">The primary educational goal that most accurately describes the student’s reason for enrollment at the reporting institution.  Community colleges are required to report this information and should collect it for each student during each registration period. </descrip>
		<descrip type="example">[SIRIS STUDENT element SE180] </descrip>
		<descrip type="example">SIRIS reporting codes are as follows: </descrip>
		<descrip type="example"> 1  Transfer to another SUNY college after earning a degree </descrip>
		<descrip type="example"> 2  Transfer to a non-SUNY college after earning a degree </descrip>
		<descrip type="example"> 3  Transfer to a SUNY college without earning a degree </descrip>
		<descrip type="example"> 4  Transfer to a non-SUNY college without earning a degree </descrip>
		<descrip type="example"> 5  Earn a degree/certificate and seek employment rather than pursue further post-secondary education </descrip>
		<descrip type="example"> 6  Learn new skills or upgrade existing skills without earning a degree </descrip>
		<descrip type="example"> 7  Seek enrichment rather than to pursue a degree/certificate </descrip>
		<descrip type="example"> 8  Obtain a Certificate of General Education Development (GED) through the accumulation of college credits </descrip>
		<descrip type="example"> 9  Uncertain; student has not determined his/her educational goal at this time </descrip>
		<descrip type="example">10 Student has not responded to the request for goal information or student goal is not applicable to the student </descrip>
	</langSet>
</termEntry>
<termEntry>
	<langSet xml:lang="en">
		<ntig>
			<termGrp>
				<term>STUDENT IN A BACCALAUREATE DEGREE PROGRAM</term>
			</termGrp>
		</ntig>
		<descrip type="definition">A CREDIT COURSE STUDENT who has met the requirements for admission to a bachelor's degree PROGRAM and who in the reporting term is carrying out a planned sequence of courses toward that degree.  Included are students who may have not yet chosen a specific field of study.  </descrip>
		<descrip type="example">[See SIRIS STUDENT elements SE030 ACADEMIC PROGRAM ID – PRIMARY and SE035 ACADEMIC AWARD LEVEL – PRIMARY]  </descrip>
	</langSet>
</termEntry>
<termEntry>
	<langSet xml:lang="en">
		<ntig>
			<termGrp>
				<term>STUDENT IN A DOCTORAL DEGREE PROGRAM</term>
			</termGrp>
		</ntig>
		<descrip type="definition">A CREDIT COURSE STUDENT who has met the requirements for admission to a doctoral degree PROGRAM (except AudD, DDS, DNP, DPT, DVM, JD, MD, PharmD, OD, and OTD programs) and who in the reporting term is carrying out a planned sequence of courses leading to a doctoral degree.  </descrip>
		<descrip type="example">[See SIRIS STUDENT elements SE030 ACADEMIC PROGRAM ID – PRIMARY and SE035 ACADEMIC AWARD LEVEL – PRIMARY]  </descrip>
	</langSet>
</termEntry>
<termEntry>
	<langSet xml:lang="en">
		<ntig>
			<termGrp>
				<term>STUDENT IN A FIRST-PROFESSIONAL DEGREE PROGRAM</term>
			</termGrp>
		</ntig>
		<descrip type="definition">A CREDIT COURSE STUDENT who has met the requirements for admission to a AudD (Audiology), DDS (Dentistry), DNP (Nursing Practice), DPT (Physical Therapy), DVM (Vet Med), JD (Law), MD (Medical), PharmD (Pharmacy), OD (Optometry), or OTD (Occupational Therapy) program and who in the reporting term is carrying out a planned sequence of courses leading to one of these degrees.   </descrip>
		<descrip type="example">[See SIRIS STUDENT elements SE030 ACADEMIC PROGRAM ID – PRIMARY and SE035 ACADEMIC AWARD LEVEL – PRIMARY]  </descrip>
	</langSet>
</termEntry>
<termEntry>
	<langSet xml:lang="en">
		<ntig>
			<termGrp>
				<term>STUDENT IN A GRADUATE CERTIFICATE PROGRAM</term>
			</termGrp>
		</ntig>
		<descrip type="definition">A CREDIT COURSE STUDENT who has met the requirements for admission to a &quot;Certificate of Advanced Study&quot; program and who in the reporting term is carrying out a planned sequence of courses leading to a graduate certificate.  </descrip>
		<descrip type="example">[See SIRIS STUDENT elements SE030 ACADEMIC PROGRAM ID – PRIMARY and SE035 ACADEMIC AWARD LEVEL – PRIMARY]  </descrip>
		<descrip type="example">[See also STUDENT IN A POST-BACCALAUREATE GRADUATE CERTIFICATE PROGRAM and STUDENT IN A POST-MASTERS GRADUATE CERTIFICATE PROGRAM] </descrip>
	</langSet>
</termEntry>
<termEntry>
	<langSet xml:lang="en">
		<ntig>
			<termGrp>
				<term>STUDENT IN A HEALTH FIRST-PROFESSIONAL DEGREE PROGRAM</term>
			</termGrp>
		</ntig>
		<descrip type="definition">A CREDIT COURSE STUDENT who has met the requirements for admission to a AudD (Audiology), DDS (Dentistry), DNP (Nursing Practice), DPT (Physical Therapy), DVM (Vet Med), MD (Medical), PharmD (Pharmacy), OD (Optometry), or OTD (Occupational Therapy) and who in the reporting term is carrying out a planned sequence of courses leading to one of these degrees.   </descrip>
		<descrip type="example">[See SIRIS STUDENT elements SE030 ACADEMIC PROGRAM ID – PRIMARY and SE035 ACADEMIC AWARD LEVEL – PRIMARY]  </descrip>
	</langSet>
</termEntry>
<termEntry>
	<langSet xml:lang="en">
		<ntig>
			<termGrp>
				<term>STUDENT IN A MASTER'S DEGREE PROGRAM</term>
			</termGrp>
		</ntig>
		<descrip type="definition">A CREDIT COURSE STUDENT who has met the requirements for admission to a master's degree PROGRAM and who in the reporting term is carrying out a planned sequence of course toward a master's degree.  Include students in this category even though they may not have been admitted to &quot;candidacy&quot;.  </descrip>
		<descrip type="example">[See SIRIS STUDENT elements SE030 ACADEMIC PROGRAM ID – PRIMARY and SE035 ACADEMIC AWARD LEVEL – PRIMARY]  </descrip>
	</langSet>
</termEntry>
<termEntry>
	<langSet xml:lang="en">
		<ntig>
			<termGrp>
				<term>STUDENT IN A MICROCREDENTIAL</term>
			</termGrp>
		</ntig>
		<descrip type="definition">An individual enrolled in a MICROCREDENTIAL.  Such a student must be enrolled in the reporting term and carrying out a course or planned sequence of courses leading to a microcredential awarded by the reporting institution.  The student can be enrolled in a credit-bearing or non-credit-bearing microcredential. </descrip>
		<descrip type="example">[See SIRIS STUDENT element SE045] </descrip>
	</langSet>
</termEntry>
<termEntry>
	<langSet xml:lang="en">
		<ntig>
			<termGrp>
				<term>STUDENT IN A POST-BACCALAUREATE GRADUATE CERTIFICATE PROGRAM</term>
			</termGrp>
		</ntig>
		<descrip type="definition">A CREDIT COURSE STUDENT enrolled in a graduate certificate program which does not require a master’s degree as a prerequisite for entry into the program.  Such a student must also be this term carrying out a planned sequence of courses leading to a certificate awarded by the reporting institution.   </descrip>
		<descrip type="example">[See SIRIS STUDENT elements SE030 ACADEMIC PROGRAM ID - PRIMARY and SE035 ACADEMIC AWARD LEVEL - PRIMARY] </descrip>
	</langSet>
</termEntry>
<termEntry>
	<langSet xml:lang="en">
		<ntig>
			<termGrp>
				<term>STUDENT IN A POST-MASTERS GRADUATE CERTIFICATE PROGRAM</term>
			</termGrp>
		</ntig>
		<descrip type="definition">A CREDIT COURSE STUDENT enrolled in a graduate certificate PROGRAM which requires a master’s degree as a prerequisite for entry into the program.  Such a student must also be this term carrying out a planned sequence of courses leading to a certificate awarded by your institution.   </descrip>
		<descrip type="example">[See SIRIS STUDENT elements SE030 ACADEMIC PROGRAM ID - PRIMARY and SE035 ACADEMIC AWARD LEVEL - PRIMARY] </descrip>
	</langSet>
</termEntry>
<termEntry>
	<langSet xml:lang="en">
		<ntig>
			<termGrp>
				<term>STUDENT IN AN ASSOCIATE DEGREE PROGRAM</term>
			</termGrp>
		</ntig>
		<descrip type="definition">A CREDIT COURSE STUDENT who has met the requirements for admission to an associate degree PROGRAM and who in the reporting term is carrying out a planned sequence of courses toward that degree.  Included are students who may have not yet chosen a specific field of study.  </descrip>
		<descrip type="example">[See SIRIS STUDENT elements SE030 ACADEMIC PROGRAM ID – PRIMARY and SE035 ACADEMIC AWARD LEVEL – PRIMARY]  </descrip>
	</langSet>
</termEntry>
<termEntry>
	<langSet xml:lang="en">
		<ntig>
			<termGrp>
				<term>STUDENT IN AN UNDERGRADUATE DIPLOMA OR CERTIFICATE PROGRAM</term>
			</termGrp>
		</ntig>
		<descrip type="definition">A CREDIT COURSE STUDENT who has met the requirements for admission to a diploma or certificate PROGRAM which requires one or more terms of full-time work or its equivalent.  Such a student must also be in the reporting term carrying out a planned sequence of courses leading to a diploma or certificate awarded by the reporting institution.   </descrip>
		<descrip type="example">[See SIRIS STUDENT elements SE030 ACADEMIC PROGRAM ID – PRIMARY and SE035 ACADEMIC AWARD LEVEL – PRIMARY]  </descrip>
	</langSet>
</termEntry>
<termEntry>
	<langSet xml:lang="en">
		<ntig>
			<termGrp>
				<term>STUDENT LEVEL</term>
			</termGrp>
		</ntig>
		<descrip type="definition">A category that reflects both a student’s academic progress and matriculation status.    </descrip>
				<descrip type="example">Categories are as follow: </descrip>
		<descrip type="example">FRESHMAN </descrip>
		<descrip type="example">SOPHOMORE  </descrip>
		<descrip type="example">UNDERGRADUATE, NOT IN A PROGRAM  </descrip>
		<descrip type="example">JUNIOR  </descrip>
		<descrip type="example">SENIOR   </descrip>
		<descrip type="example">BEGINNING GRADUATE </descrip>
		<descrip type="example">ADVANCED GRADUATE </descrip>
		<descrip type="example">HEALTH FIRST PROFESSIONAL </descrip>
		<descrip type="example">[Derived from SIRIS STUDENT elements SE030 ACADEMIC PROGRAM ID – PRIMARY and SE110 ACCUMULATED CREDIT HOURS]  </descrip>
	</langSet>
</termEntry>
<termEntry>
	<langSet xml:lang="en">
		<ntig>
			<termGrp>
				<term>STUDENT LOCAL ID</term>
			</termGrp>
		</ntig>
		<descrip type="definition">The Student ID assigned by a campus for use on its local data system.  Required for the assignment of a SUNY ID.  Used for SIRIS matching purposes.   </descrip>
		<descrip type="example">[SIRIS STUDENT element SD030, TERM SECTION element TE010, DEGREE element DS030] </descrip>
	</langSet>
</termEntry>
<termEntry>
	<langSet xml:lang="en">
		<ntig>
			<termGrp>
				<term>STUDENT OPINION SURVEY (SOS)</term>
			</termGrp>
		</ntig>
		<descrip type="definition">A SUNY-specific survey administered in conjunction with ACT (American College Testing program) that measures student attitudes and opinions on significant aspects of the collegiate experiences (e.g. academic, student life, facilities, services).  Typically administered every three years during the spring semester.  The current administration is 4-year schools one year, 2-year schools the next year, and then an off-year.   
		The last academic year for administration of the SOS was 2018-19.  This survey was replaced by the in-house STUDENT SATISFACTION SURVEY (SSS). </descrip>
	</langSet>
</termEntry>
<termEntry>
	<langSet xml:lang="en">
		<ntig>
			<termGrp>
				<term>STUDENT RIGHT-TO-KNOW</term>
			</termGrp>
		</ntig>
		<descrip type="definition">Also known as the "Student Right-to-Know and Campus Security Act" (P.L. 101-542), which was passed by Congress November 9, 1990. Title I, Section 103, requires institutions eligible for Title IV funding to calculate completion or graduation rates of certificate- or degree-seeking, full-time students entering that institution, and to disclose these rates to all students and prospective students. Further, Section 104 requires each institution that participates in any Title IV program and is attended by students receiving athletically-related student aid to submit a report to the Secretary of Education annually.  This report is to contain, among other things, graduation/completion rates of all students as well as students receiving athletically-related student aid by race/ethnicity and gender and by sport, and the average completion or graduation rate for the four most recent years.  These data are also required to be disclosed to parents, coaches, and potential student athletes when the institution offers athletically-related student aid.  The Graduation Rates component of IPEDS was developed specifically to help institutions respond to these requirements. </descrip>
	</langSet>
</termEntry>
<termEntry>
	<langSet xml:lang="en">
		<ntig>
			<termGrp>
				<term>STUDENT SATISFACTION SURVEY (SSS)</term>
			</termGrp>
		</ntig>
		<descrip type="definition">A SUNY-specific survey created and administered by SUNY System Administration in conjunction with campus institutional research representatives that measures student attitudes and opinions on various key aspects of the collegiate experiences (e.g. academic, student life, facilities, services).  The SSS was first administered in spring 2021 as a replacement to the STUDENT OPINION SURVEY (SOS) which was a survey administered in conjunction with ACT.  The SSS was created in a way so that comparisons, to the extent possible, can be made between previous iterations of the SOS and the new SSS.  SSS is to be administered every two to three years during the spring semester.  The current administration includes both 2-year and 4-year institutions. 
			The Student Satisfaction Survey (SSS) was introduced in academic year 2020-21 and replaced the long-standing STUDENT OPINION SURVEY (SOS). </descrip>
	</langSet>
</termEntry>
<termEntry>
	<langSet xml:lang="en">
		<ntig>
			<termGrp>
				<term>STUDENT VETERAN</term>
			</termGrp>
		</ntig>
		<descrip type="definition">A CREDIT COURSE STUDENT who is a military veteran enrolled at the reporting institution and who is receiving veterans benefits for which the institution must certify his/her enrollment.  </descrip>
		<descrip type="example">[See SIRIS STUDENT element SS160 MILITARY SERVICE STATUS] </descrip>
	</langSet>
</termEntry>
<termEntry>
	<langSet xml:lang="en">
		<ntig>
			<termGrp>
				<term>STUDENT/FACULTY FTE RATIO</term>
			</termGrp>
		</ntig>
		<descrip type="definition">A ratio calculated by dividing the FULL-TIME EQUIVALENT STUDENT WORKLOAD by the FULL-TIME EQUIVALENT FACULTY.  i.e. FTE STUDENT WORKLOAD / FTE FACULTY  </descrip>
	</langSet>
</termEntry>
<termEntry>
	<langSet xml:lang="en">
		<ntig>
			<termGrp>
				<term>STUDENTS WITH DISABILITIES</term>
			</termGrp>
		</ntig>
		<descrip type="definition">Students who are mobility impaired, visually impaired, acoustically impaired, or having any of the following handicapping conditions.  The following definitions of disability categories are those provided by the State Education Department (as of October 13, 2017). 
		Disability Categories and Sub-Categories:   
		A. Neurodevelopmental  
			a. ADHD  
			b. Autism Spectrum Disorder (including Asperger’s Syndrome)  
			c. Communication/Speech: communication disorders including apraxia of speech, articulation disorder, phonemic disorder, stuttering, voice disorder  
			d. Learning Disability: includes central auditory processing disorder, disorder of written expression, dysgraphia, dyscalculia, dyslexia, learning disorder NOS, mathematics disorder, mixed receptive-expressive language disorder, nonverbal learning disorder (if student has not been diagnosed on the autism spectrum), processing speed disorder, reading disorder, visual processing disorder  
			e. Motor: developmental coordination disorder, stereotypical movement disorders, tic disorders, tremors  
		B. Sensory  
			a. Blind: visual acuity of 20/200 or worse in the better or stronger eye with the best correction; totally blind; or a person with 20 degrees or less field of vision (pinhole vision).  
			b. Low Vision: visual acuity of 20/70 or worse in the better eye with best correction, a total field loss of 140 degrees or more in the field of vision, difficulty in reading regular newsprint even with vision corrected by glasses or contact lenses, loss of vision in one eye  
			c. Deaf: not able to discern spoken communication by sound alone, a hearing loss that prevents one from totally receiving sounds through the ear, whether permanent or fluctuating  
			d. Hard of Hearing: partial hearing loss, may be conductive, sensorineural, or both  
		C. Mental Health  
			Generally, disorders characterized by dysregulation of mood, thought, and/or behavior. These include anxiety disorders, eating disorders, mood disorders and psychotic disorders.  
		D. Physical  
			a. Basic Chronic Medical Condition: a medical condition resulting in limited strength, vitality or alertness due to chronic or acute health problems. This would not include those with temporary disabilities.  
			b. Mobility: a student who, typically, must use a standard manual or electric wheelchair or other assistive devices (walker, crutches, braces, prosthesis, etc.) to move from place to place. Students must be counted in another category, such as orthopedic or basic or complex chronic medical conditions. This would not include those with temporary disabilities. Do not include numbers from this category in the Multiple Disabilities count.  
			c. Orthopedic: a physical disability caused by congenital anomaly, by diseases of the bones and muscles, connective tissue disorders, or from other causes. This would not include those with temporary disabilities.  
		E. Intersystem (existing between two or more systems)  
			a. Alcohol/substance addiction and recovery: students who are recovering from drug or alcohol or substance abuse or who are in treatment programs  
			b. Complex Chronic Medical Condition: a medical condition that significantly affects multiple systems of the body. This would not include those with temporary disabilities.  
			c. Traumatic brain injury: an injury caused by an external physical force (concussion) or from certain medical conditions (aneurysm, anoxia brain tumors, encephalitis, stroke) with resulting mild, moderate or severe disabilities in one or more areas (abstract thinking, attention, cognition, information processing, judgment, language, memory, motor abilities, perceptual, physical functions, problem solving, psychosocial behavior, reasoning, sensory, speech). The term does not include injuries that are congenital or birth related. This would not include those with temporary disabilities.  
		F. Temporary Disabilities  
			A transitory impairment with an actual or expected duration of six months or less. Examples include bone fractures, sprains, torn ligaments, post-surgical recoveries, significant illness, etc. Do not include Temporary Disabilities in any other category.  
		G. Other Disabilities 
			a. Print Disability: An individual with barriers to accessing instructional materials requiring readers, note takers, and/or materials in alternate format. Individuals must require course materials in alternate formats and must require one or more of the following supports to access materials: assistive technology, specialized technology training and support, enhanced editing of digital formats, note taking that includes digital conversion, and 1:1 lab assistance in a class that requires alternative formats/readers. 
		H. Multiple Disabilities  
			a. A student with two or more disabilities, to be counted once here. Students reported in this category should be reported in every other category and/or sub-category in which they fit. For example, students with both ADHD and a Learning Disability should be listed under both categories and counted once in Multiple Disabilities. Do not include numbers from Mobility in the Multiple Disabilities count.   </descrip>
		<descrip type="example">[See SIRIS STUDENT element SS170 Disability Status]  </descrip>
	</langSet>
</termEntry>
<termEntry>
	<langSet xml:lang="en">
		<ntig>
			<termGrp>
				<term>STUDY ABROAD PROGRAM</term>
			</termGrp>
		</ntig>
		<descrip type="definition">See OVERSEAS ACADEMIC PROGRAM (OAP)  </descrip>
	</langSet>
</termEntry>
<termEntry>
	<langSet xml:lang="en">
		<ntig>
			<termGrp>
				<term>SUBCAMPUS</term>
			</termGrp>
		</ntig>
		<descrip type="definition">A concept used to allow campuses to report administrative components that are of interest for reporting purposes.     </descrip>
	</langSet>
</termEntry>
<termEntry>
	<langSet xml:lang="en">
		<ntig>
			<termGrp>
				<term>SUCCESSFUL EDUCATIONAL OUTCOMES (SEO) REPORTS</term>
			</termGrp>
		</ntig>
		<descrip type="definition">See EDUCATIONAL OUTCOMES (EO) REPORTS </descrip>
	</langSet>
</termEntry>
<termEntry>
	<langSet xml:lang="en">
		<ntig>
			<termGrp>
				<term>SUNY APPLICATION</term>
			</termGrp>
		</ntig>
		<descrip type="definition">SUNY’s own undergraduate application for first-time and transfer admissions. Data is standardized, processed centrally at System Administration, and transmitted to campuses.  As of May 2016, the SUNY App is accepted by fifty-eight SUNY campuses. See https://www.suny.edu/applysuny for more information. </descrip>
	</langSet>
</termEntry>
<termEntry>
	<langSet xml:lang="en">
		<ntig>
			<termGrp>
				<term>SUNY EXCELS</term>
			</termGrp>
		</ntig>
		<descrip type="definition">An initiative launched in 2015 that focused on five priority areas: access, completion, success, inquiry, and engagement.  Various metrics were established as a way System Administration and campuses could review historical data and set targets in each of the five priority areas.   
			SUNY Excels Executive Data Summaries were created as a reference document to reference and monitor key performance indicators system-wide and for each sector and individual campus.   
			See https://www.system.suny.edu/institutional-research/resources/ for more information. </descrip>
	</langSet>
</termEntry>
<termEntry>
	<langSet xml:lang="en">
		<ntig>
			<termGrp>
				<term>SUNY EXECUTIVE DATA SUMMARIES</term>
			</termGrp>
		</ntig>
		<descrip type="definition">Reports stemming from the SUNY Excels initiative where various metrics were established as a way System Administration and campuses could review historical data and set targets in each of the five priority areas.  The SUNY Executive Data Summaries kept many of the initial SUNY Excels metrics in place and added several new metrics.  The SUNY Executive Data Summaries serve as a resource document to reference and monitor key performance indicators system-wide, for each sector, and for each individual campus.  The SUNY Executive Data Summaries are typically updated twice a year, in January and June.   
			See https://www.system.suny.edu/institutional-research/resources/ for more information. </descrip>
	</langSet>
</termEntry>
<termEntry>
	<langSet xml:lang="en">
		<ntig>
			<termGrp>
				<term>SUNY FAST FACTS</term>
			</termGrp>
		</ntig>
		<descrip type="definition">A webpage on the SUNY.edu website that provides static broad enrollment, completion, graduation rate, tuition, and research data for the University.  In addition, the webpage provides links to various interactive dashboards to provide a more detailed view of enrollment, online enrollment, demographics, completions, graduation rate, student residence, and research data.  The SUNY Fast Facts dashboards and webpage are updated annually. 
			See https://www.suny.edu/about/fast-facts/  </descrip>
	</langSet>
</termEntry>
<termEntry>
	<langSet xml:lang="en">
		<ntig>
			<termGrp>
				<term>SUNY GRADWAGES</term>
			</termGrp>
		</ntig>
		<descrip type="definition">A dashboard created by the SUNY System Administration Office of Institutional Research and Data Analytics to provide information to the public about the wages of SUNY graduates.  Wages data come from the New York State Department of Labor (NYS DOL) Unemployment Insurance (UI) System.  These data include around 97 percent of New York’s non-farm employment.  The wages presented in the SUNY gradwages dashboard are derived from previous years' combined academic and employment data and are intended to illustrate the potential earnings by program of study based on recent SUNY graduate employment outcomes.   
			The data only includes the wages reported to the UI System.  Categories of employment not covered by UI include the self-employed, most federal employees including military, and several small categories of employment. 
			See https://www.suny.edu/gradwages/ .  </descrip>
	</langSet>
</termEntry>
<termEntry>
	<langSet xml:lang="en">
		<ntig>
			<termGrp>
				<term>SUNY ID</term>
			</termGrp>
		</ntig>
		<descrip type="definition">A unique identifier assigned by SUNY System Administration to SUNY students and employees.  Used for SIRIS matching purposes.   </descrip>
		<descrip type="example">[SIRIS STUDENT element SD040, SIRIS DEGREE element DS025, SIRIS TERM SECTION element TF030, SIRIS TERM SECTION element TE020] </descrip>
		<descrip type="example">In order to assign a Student SUNY ID, the following data elements are required:</descrip>
		<descrip type="example">Student’s Local ID </descrip>
		<descrip type="example">Date of Birth (required if SSN is not reported) </descrip>
		<descrip type="example">Gender </descrip>
		<descrip type="example">Last Name (required if first name is blank) </descrip>
		<descrip type="example">First Name (required if last name is blank) </descrip>
		<descrip type="example">See SIRIS Appendix P for more details. </descrip>
	</langSet>
</termEntry>
<termEntry>
	<langSet xml:lang="en">
		<ntig>
			<termGrp>
				<term>SUNY KOREA</term>
			</termGrp>
		</ntig>
		<descrip type="definition">SUNY Korea was established in March 2012 as the first American university system in Incheon, South Korea. In 2012, Stony Brook University began to offer programs in South Korea as part of the Ministry of Education’s decision to serve the transnational needs for quality and global education. In 2017, Fashion Institute of Technology (FIT), began also offering programs at SUNY Korea. Currently, SUNY Korea offers undergraduate and graduate degree programs in Computer Science, Mechanical Engineering, Technological Systems Management, Applied Mathematics and Statistics, Business Management, and Electrical Engineering from Stony Brook University (SBU) and associate programs in Fashion Design and Fashion Business Management from Fashion Institute of Technology (FIT). Students of SUNY Korea can expect to experience the authentic American higher education, and they can choose to take courses in both South Korea and the U.S. </descrip>
	</langSet>
</termEntry>
<termEntry>
	<langSet xml:lang="en">
		<ntig>
			<termGrp>
				<term>SUNY ONLINE</term>
			</termGrp>
		</ntig>
		<descrip type="definition">A collaboration between SUNY System Administration and a cohort of SUNY campuses that offers associate, bachelors, and master’s degree programs online.  SUNY Online degree pathways don't encompass all the available online degree programs and online course offerings throughout the 64 SUNY campuses.  It offers a special group of degree programs in concentrations that allow students to start or finish a degree at any point in their lives and academic journey. SUNY Online provides administrative support for the campuses and student supports for the students enrolled in the course offered by those campuses.   
			SUNY Online success coaches act as an online concierge for students in some of the following areas: 
			- Advising and registration 
			- Tutoring support 
			- Buying books 
			- Locating campus resources such as career services, mental wellness, and student accounts 
			- Hosting community and success webinars for online learners </descrip>
	</langSet>
</termEntry>
<termEntry>
	<langSet xml:lang="en">
		<ntig>
			<termGrp>
				<term>SUPPORTING DOCUMENTS</term>
			</termGrp>
		</ntig>
		<descrip type="definition">Collection of memoranda and other documents representing SUNY policies regarding the uniform reporting of enrollment, degrees, and student and faculty workload.  For additional information, see https://system.suny.edu/academic-affairs/mtp/ .</descrip>
	</langSet>
</termEntry>
<termEntry>
	<langSet xml:lang="en">
		<ntig>
			<termGrp>
				<term>SUTRA (STATE UNIVERSITY TUITION REIMBURSABLE ACCOUNT)</term>
			</termGrp>
		</ntig>
		<descrip type="definition">For State-Operated institutions only.  SUTRA comprises four separate credit bearing income fund reimbursable types of activities: 
			- Summer Session (self supporting) 
			- Overseas Academic Programs (excluding EXCHANGE STUDENTS) 
			- Contract Courses (see CONTRACT COURSES) 
			- Academic Year (Fall/Spring) overflow enrollment  
			See SUPPORTING DOCUMENT “Policy Procedures on State University Tuition Reimbursable Accounts for Credit Bearing Activities” dated May 1993.  </descrip>
	</langSet>
</termEntry>
<termEntry>
	<langSet xml:lang="en">
		<ntig>
			<termGrp>
				<term>TEACHER CERTIFICATION COURSE</term>
			</termGrp>
		</ntig>
		<descrip type="definition">A course that is a “methods” course, “pre-practicum” course, student teaching course, or other required teacher certification course (other than content-specific courses which are required to teach in a specific field). </descrip>
		<descrip type="example">[See SIRIS COURSE element CC080] </descrip>
	</langSet>
</termEntry>
<termEntry>
	<langSet xml:lang="en">
		<ntig>
			<termGrp>
				<term>TOTAL CREDIT HOURS</term>
			</termGrp>
		</ntig>
		<descrip type="definition">For the term being reported, the number of attempted credit hours associated with courses meeting the reporting standards as defined in SIRIS Appendix O.  Courses dropped during the add/drop period are excluded.  Included are withdrawals that take place after the CENSUS DATE, REMEDIAL courses with EQUIVALENT CREDIT HOURS, contract and other self-supported credit courses, and any credits attempted under a recognized CROSS-REGISTRATION agreement.  Used to determine a student’s workload status (i.e. FULL-TIME STUDENT, PART-TIME STUDENT) when arraying official HEADCOUNT reports. </descrip>
		<descrip type="example">[SIRIS STUDENT element SE070] </descrip>
	</langSet>
</termEntry>
<termEntry>
	<langSet xml:lang="en">
		<ntig>
			<termGrp>
				<term>TRANSFER STUDENT</term>
			</termGrp>
		</ntig>
		<descrip type="definition">An UNDERGRADUATE STUDENT who is enrolled at the reporting institution for the first time in the current term but who has attended another college or university prior to the current term. The actual number of CREDIT HOURS the student is allowed to transfer is not relevant to the distinction between a transfer student and a FIRST-TIME STUDENT, even if no credits were ultimately transferable.  
			A student who moves from one level of study to another at the same institution (e. g. from an associate’s degree program to a baccalaureate degree program) is not considered a transfer student but rather a TRANSITION STUDENT.  
			A student who has only changed his or her field of study without changing institutions is not a transfer student as here defined.  A student whose previous post-secondary education is only at a non-collegiate institution such as a business school or technical institution should be considered FIRST-TIME STUDENT unless the reporting institution expects to give credit for such activities, in which case the student is a transfer student.  </descrip>
		<descrip type="example">[See SIRIS STUDENT element SE020 HIGHER EDUCATION HISTORY] </descrip>
	</langSet>
</termEntry>
<termEntry>
	<langSet xml:lang="en">
		<ntig>
			<termGrp>
				<term>TRANSITION STUDENT</term>
			</termGrp>
		</ntig>
		<descrip type="definition">A student who was initially enrolled in an associate degree program at the reporting institution and is entering a baccalaureate program at the same institution for the first time.  Subsequent undergraduate term enrollments should be classified as CONTINUING/RETURNING. </descrip>
		<descrip type="example">[See SIRIS STUDENT element SE020 HIGHER EDUCATION HISTORY] </descrip>
	</langSet>
</termEntry>
<termEntry>
	<langSet xml:lang="en">
		<ntig>
			<termGrp>
				<term>TUITION RATE INDICATOR</term>
			</termGrp>
		</ntig>
		<descrip type="definition">The tuition status of the student in the current term, what tuition rate the student is being charged. </descrip>
		<descrip type="example">[SIRIS STUDENT element SE160] </descrip>
		<descrip type="example">SIRIS reporting codes are as follows: </descrip>
		<descrip type="example">1  In-district </descrip>
		<descrip type="example">2  Equivalent in-district </descrip>
		<descrip type="example">3  In-state   </descrip>
		<descrip type="example">4  Equivalent in-state </descrip>
		<descrip type="example">5  Out-of-state </descrip>
		<descrip type="example">6  Non-tuition </descrip>
		<descrip type="example">Note that for SIRIS reporting purposes, state-operated institutions cannot report in-district tuition rates.  Community colleges should only report in-district tuition rates if they are different from the in-state ones. </descrip>
	</langSet>
</termEntry>
<termEntry>
	<langSet xml:lang="en">
		<ntig>
			<termGrp>
				<term>UNDERGRADUATE RESEARCH</term>
			</termGrp>
		</ntig>
		<descrip type="definition">An inquiry or investigation conducted by an undergraduate student that makes an original intellectual or creative contribution to the discipline.  See www.cur.org/ for more information.  This is an Applied Learning Activity. </descrip>
	</langSet>
</termEntry>
<termEntry>
	<langSet xml:lang="en">
		<ntig>
			<termGrp>
				<term>UNDERGRADUATE STUDENT</term>
			</termGrp>
		</ntig>
		<descrip type="definition">A CREDIT COURSE STUDENT who is  
			(1) in an undergraduate program  
			OR  
			(2) not in a program, not accepted by your institution for graduate study in the current term and does not have a graduate degree 
			OR  
			(3) not in a program, not accepted by your institution for graduate study in the current term, holds a bachelor's degree and is taking only undergraduate courses.  
		[See STUDENT LEVEL] </descrip>
	</langSet>
</termEntry>
<termEntry>
	<langSet xml:lang="en">
		<ntig>
			<termGrp>
				<term>UNDERREPRESENTED (HISTORICALLY)</term>
			</termGrp>
		</ntig>
		<descrip type="definition">Refers to groups, in general, who have been denied access and/or suffered past institutional discrimination in the United States.  It includes African Americans, Asian Americans, Pacific Islanders, Hispanics or Chicanos/Latinos, and Native Americans.  Other groups in the United States currently underrepresented within the population may include but are not limited to other ethnicities; adult learners; veterans; people with disabilities; lesbian, gay, bisexual, and transgender individuals; different religious groups; and those with disadvantaged economic backgrounds. </descrip>
	</langSet>
</termEntry>
<termEntry>
	<langSet xml:lang="en">
		<ntig>
			<termGrp>
				<term>UNDERREPRESENTED MINORITIES (URM)</term>
			</termGrp>
		</ntig>
		<descrip type="definition">For SUNY reporting purposes, individuals (excluding U.S. nonresidents) who identify as being in at least one of the following race/ethnicity groups:  Hispanic, Black or African American, American Indian or Alaska Native, Native Hawaiian or Other Pacific Islander.  Persons reported with more than one race are considered to be underrepresented minorities if one or more of the races is Black or African American, American Indian or Alaska Native, Native Hawaiian or Other Pacific Islander.  [See also RACE] </descrip>
	</langSet>
</termEntry>
<termEntry>
	<langSet xml:lang="en">
		<ntig>
			<termGrp>
				<term>UNDERSERVED</term>
			</termGrp>
		</ntig>
		<descrip type="definition">Components of the population comprised of groups or constituents that are disadvantaged in relation to other groups because of social, economic, or structural obstacles that prevent inclusion and access to services.  Includes those with disabling conditions. </descrip>
	</langSet>
</termEntry>
<termEntry>
	<langSet xml:lang="en">
		<ntig>
			<termGrp>
				<term>UNDOCUMENTED ALIEN</term>
			</termGrp>
		</ntig>
		<descrip type="definition">A student who is not a United States citizen, is a resident of the US, and does not hold a valid United States VISA.   
			Undocumented aliens who have graduated from a NYS high school may be eligible to pay in-state tuition.   
			To report these students on SIRIS STUDENT, report element SS020 VISA Code = UNDOC.  These students, along with Legal Permanent Residents (VISA code = LPR), will be treated as US citizens for SUNY reporting purposes. </descrip>
	</langSet>
</termEntry>
<termEntry>
	<langSet xml:lang="en">
		<ntig>
			<termGrp>
				<term>UNKNOWN (HIGHER EDUCATION HISTORY)</term>
			</termGrp>
		</ntig>
		<descrip type="definition">A student whose enrollment history is unknown to the institution or a student whose enrollment is temporary or incidental to the institution (e.g. a student enrolling for the first time during a summer term or a cross-registered/overseas exchange student).   </descrip>
		<descrip type="example">[See SIRIS STUDENT element SE020 HIGHER EDUCATION HISTORY]   </descrip>
	</langSet>
</termEntry>
<termEntry>
	<langSet xml:lang="en">
		<ntig>
			<termGrp>
				<term>UPPER DIVISION COURSE</term>
			</termGrp>
		</ntig>
		<descrip type="definition">A course directed primarily at UPPER DIVISION STUDENTS. </descrip>
	</langSet>
</termEntry>
<termEntry>
	<langSet xml:lang="en">
		<ntig>
			<termGrp>
				<term>UPPER DIVISION STUDENT (IN A PROGRAM)</term>
			</termGrp>
		</ntig>
		<descrip type="definition">A STUDENT IN A BACCALAUREATE DEGREE PROGRAM who has accumulated more than 60 CREDIT HOURS.  An UNDERGRADUATE STUDENT in a diploma, certificate, or associate degree program is always considered a LOWER DIVISION STUDENT.  </descrip>		
	</langSet>
</termEntry>
<termEntry>
	<langSet xml:lang="en">
		<ntig>
			<termGrp>
				<term>VISA CODE</term>
			</termGrp>
		</ntig>
		<descrip type="definition">The VISA type of a non-US citizen (including Legal Permanent Residents).   </descrip>
		<descrip type="example">[SIRIS STUDENT element SS020] </descrip>
		<descrip type="example">See SIRIS Appendix H-4 for the list of current, valid codes.  This list contains VISA codes assigned by the United States Department of State as well as additional entries to accommodate special situations (e.g. UNDOCUMENTED ALIENS, unknown).   </descrip>
	</langSet>
</termEntry>
<termEntry>
	<langSet xml:lang="en">
		<ntig>
			<termGrp>
				<term>VOCATIONAL PREPARATION</term>
			</termGrp>
		</ntig>
		<descrip type="definition">Courses designed to provide education, training, or retraining in one or more semi-skilled, skilled, technical, or other occupational categories to prepare the student for entrance into a particular chosen vocation, upgrading of present employment opportunity, or achievement of other career goals.  </descrip>
	</langSet>
</termEntry>
<termEntry>
	<langSet xml:lang="en">
		<ntig>
			<termGrp>
				<term>VOLUNTARY FRAMEWORK OF ACCOUNTABILITY (VFA)</term>
			</termGrp>
		</ntig>
		<descrip type="definition">The VFA is an accountability framework for community colleges created by community college leaders and facilitated by the American Association of Community Colleges (AACC). The VFA differs from accountability frameworks traditionally used for 4-year institutions and is meant to capture the unique mission of community colleges and the diversity of student’s goals and educational experiences. </descrip>
	</langSet>
</termEntry>
<termEntry>
	<langSet xml:lang="en">
		<ntig>
			<termGrp>
				<term>VOLUNTARY SYSTEM OF ACCOUNTABILITY (VSA)</term>
			</termGrp>
		</ntig>
		<descrip type="definition">The VSA is a joint project of the Association of Public and Land-grant Universities (APLU) and the American Association of State Colleges and Universities (AASCU) in collaboration with the higher education community designed to increase the accountability and transparency of public 4-year colleges and universities. College Portrait  —VSA’s signature initiative— is a website that provides information on institutional and student characteristics, attendance costs, student engagement, and educational outcomes of over 260 public colleges and universities nationwide.  </descrip>
	</langSet>
</termEntry>
<termEntry>
	<langSet xml:lang="en">
		<ntig>
			<termGrp>
				<term>WICHE (WESTERN INTERSTATE COMMISSION FOR HIGHER EDUCATION)</term>
			</termGrp>
		</ntig>
		<descrip type="definition">A regional organization of states in the western United States created to facilitate resource sharing among the higher education systems of the West.  One of the initiatives WICHE coordinates is the Multistate Longitudinal Data Exchange or MLDE. </descrip>
	</langSet>
</termEntry>
<termEntry>
	<langSet xml:lang="en">
		<ntig>
			<termGrp>
				<term>WRITING INTENSIVE</term>
			</termGrp>
		</ntig>
		<descrip type="definition">A course section attribute used to describe when the majority or entirety of the requirements for successful completion of the section involve the student's completing multi-page writing assignments such as journal entries, reports, essays, research papers, etc.   
			Note that it is not necessary for all of the writing assignments to be graded in order for a section to be considered writing intensive. </descrip>
	</langSet>
</termEntry>


</body>
</text>